<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The purity of Gospel communion, or, Grounds and reasons for separation from persons of corrupt manners, or that hold erroneous doctrine in matters of faith essential to salvation, or that are guilty of false worship, or irregular administration of Gospel ordinances briefly discussed to prevent the increase of sin and disorder by a mixed communion in church fellowship / by Isaac Marlow.</title>
            <author>Marlow, Isaac.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 133 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51995</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M694</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18243</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11871364</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11871364</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50130</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51995)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50130)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 501:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The purity of Gospel communion, or, Grounds and reasons for separation from persons of corrupt manners, or that hold erroneous doctrine in matters of faith essential to salvation, or that are guilty of false worship, or irregular administration of Gospel ordinances briefly discussed to prevent the increase of sin and disorder by a mixed communion in church fellowship / by Isaac Marlow.</title>
                  <author>Marlow, Isaac.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 82 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Astwood for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. 82.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:50130:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50130:1"/>
            <head>THE PURITY OF Goſpel Communion, OR Grounds and Reaſons FOR SEPARATION From Perſons of Corrupt Manners, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHen the Lord of old brought up the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of the Land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> he ſeparated them from other Nations, to be his People in a peculiar Covenant; and by his Laws he ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified them from all Uncleanneſs;<note place="margin">Lev. 11.25. Lev. 5.2, 3. Ch. 11.24, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Numb. 19.11, 13. Deut. 23.10, to 19.</note> inſomuch that whoſo bore the Carkaſs of any unclean Beaſt, he was to waſh his Cloaths and be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean until the Even. And whoſo touched the Body of a Dead Man, &amp; purified not himſelf, he defiled the Tabernacle of the Lord; &amp; that Soal was to be cut off from <hi>Iſrael,</hi> becauſe the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50130:2"/>Water of Separation was not ſprinkled upon him.<note place="margin">Exod. 12.19. Lev. 22.3, to 8. Numb. 15.30, 31.</note> And whoſoever eat the Paſſover with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leavened Bread, or went unto the Holy things, having his uncleanneſs upon him; that Soul was to be cut off from the Congregation of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> and from the preſence of the Lord. And the Soul that diſpiſed the Word of the Lord, and brake his Commandments, that Soul was utterly to be cut off, &amp; his Iniquity ſhould be upon him. Now thoſe Separations and theſe, and many other legal cleanſings were ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows of Goſpel things, whereby the Purity of the New Teſtament Church was ſet forth. And to the end it ſhould be a Royal Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.9.</note> an Holy Nation, a peculiar People to ſhew forth the Praiſes of him, who hath called us out of darkneſs into his marvellous Light. He hath left us Holy Laws for the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Church,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.6, 7. Gal. 5.9.</note> and for the purging out of the old leaven of Unrighteouſneſs, for a little leaven leaveneth the whole Lump, as it conſequently follows; that ſuch who bear with Sin in one, cannot avoid bearing it in another; and by opening of this Sluce, a Flood of Sin and Iniquity will quickly ſweep away the beauty of a Goſpel Church; and turn the noble Vine that was planted wholly a right ſeed,<note place="margin">Jer. 2.21.</note> into the degenerate plant of a ſtrange Vine, to the diſhonour of God, the reproach of true Religion, the ſtumbling of weak Chriſtians and the hardning of one another in their Sins, and Diſobedience againſt the moſt Soveraign Majeſty of Heaven and Earth. To prevent which evils, I ſhall therefore Treat
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50130:2"/>of the way and means appointed by Chriſt, who <hi>loved the Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 1.4. Ch. 5.25, 26, 27. Tit. 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>and gave himſelf for it: That he might ſanctifie and cleanſe it with the waſhing of Water, by the Word. That he might preſent it to himſelf a glorious Church; not having ſpot or wrinkle, or any ſuch thing; but that we ſhould be holy, and without blame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him in Love.</hi> And in order thereunto, I ſhall here Premiſe, that foraſmuch as the Church of Chriſt is ſaid to be <hi>the pillar and ground of Truth,</hi> And that it is <hi>Gods building:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.15. 1 Cor. 3.9. Heb. 8.5. 1 Pet. 2.4, 5. Eph. 2.20, 21, 22. Ch. 4.4, 5. Judge 20.</note> It cannot be ſo, unleſs it be erected accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Pattern ſhewed in the Holy Mount and recorded for the Example of after A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. That every ſtone ſhould be a lively Stone by Regeneration, built up together a ſpiritual houſe in one moſt Holy Faith; for as there is one Body and one Spirit, ſo there is one Faith: And it is the Duty of every Chriſtian to help build up Gods ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Temple, according to the pure Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive and Apoſtolical Pattern, and to this end they ſhould come out from among them and be ſeparate,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.16, 17.</note> and joyn themſelves to ſuch a Congregation of Believers, where they may continue together <hi>in the Apoſtles Doctrine and Fellowſhip,</hi> (tho' not perſonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with them) and in breaking of Bread, and in Prayers. For the Church of Chriſt ſhould not be a mixed Building (tho' on Chriſt the true Foundation) as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle warneth us ſaying, <hi>Ye are Gods building,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.9, 10, 11.</note> 
               <hi>according to the Grace of God which is given un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, as a wiſe Maſter-builder, I have laid
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50130:3"/>the Foundation, and another buildeth thereon, but let every Man take heed how he buildeth thereupon; for other Foundation can no man lay, then that is laid, which is Jeſus Chriſt. Now if any man build upon this Foundation, Gold, ſilver, precious ſtones, wood, hay, ſtubble: E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very mans work ſhall be made manifeſt — and the fire ſhall try every mans work, of what ſort it is. If any mans work abide which he hath built thereupon, he ſhall receive a reward. If any mans work ſhall be burnt, he ſhall ſuffer loſs.</hi> So that the Goſpel Church is not to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of ſuch mixed and combuſtible matter as men pleaſe,<note place="margin">Rev. 1.20. 1 Pet. 1.7. Exod. 25.81. Rev. 3.18.</note> but of pure Gold, yea of ſuch as is tryed in the Fire. But to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> I ſhall prove, that it is the Duty of a Church of Chriſt to withdraw their Communion from, yea, and to purge out thoſe Perſons that are (without Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for it) guilty of corrupt Manners or evil Actions;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.1, to 6. 1 Tim. 1.20.</note> and that not only for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the groſſer ſort of Sins, as Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or inceſtuous Marriages, Blaſphemy or other notorious Evil, but for ſmaller offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. And firſt our Lord hath commanded us ſaying,<note place="margin">Math. 18.15, 16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>If thy Brother ſhall treſpaſs againſt thee, go and tell him his fault between thee and him alone: If he ſhall hear thee, thou haſt gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thy Brother. But if he will not hear thee, then take with thee one or two more, that in the Mouth of two or three Witneſſes every Word may be eſtabliſhed. And if he ſhall neglect to hear them, tell it unto the Church: but if he
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50130:3"/>neglect to hear the Church, let him be unto thee as an Heathen Man and a Publican.</hi> To which I ſhall only here ſay, that as this treſpaſs mentioned in the Text, muſt be ſome breach of the Moral Law,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.12</note> in not doing to others, as we would that others ſhould do to us; becauſe it is a treſpaſs againſt a Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: So it is plain, that for ſuch a cauſe of doing wrong, if ſatisfaction be not given by Repentance, the offender ſhould be unto us as an Heathen Man and a Publican, with whom it was not lawful to hold any Church Communion, unleſs they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is ſaid, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Now we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you, Brethren, in the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that ye withdraw your ſelves from every Brother that walketh diſorderly, and not after the Traditions which he received of us.</hi> Here we have a general command to withdraw from all diſorderly Perſons, which becauſe I deſign to open it more at large in ſome fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing part of this Treatiſe, I ſhall at preſent only note this Scripture, as a poſitive Law to preſerve the Purity of Church Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and the Words of our Lord before reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted are for the ſame end,<note place="margin">Math. 18 15, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> tho' they more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly reſpect corrupt Manners, or immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Wrongs and offences of Brethren againſt Brethren; comprehending a Prohibition of leſſer as well as groſſer Evils, as appears from the Authority of other Scriptures, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.1. <hi>Thou ſhalt not raiſe a falſe report, put not thine hand with the Wicked to be an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50130:4"/>Witneſs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 15.2, 3.</note> And <hi>David</hi> ſhews us, who ſhall abide in the Lords Tabernacle, and who ſhall dwell in his Holy Hill: <hi>He that walketh uprightly — he that backbiteth not with his Tongue, nor doeth evil to his Neighbour, nor taketh up a reproach againſt his Neighbour,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>Pſalm</hi> 101.5. <hi>Whoſo privily ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth his Neighbour, him will I cut off.</hi> And the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.8. <hi>And not rather as we be ſlanderouſly reported, and as ſome af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that we ſay, let us do evil, that good may come? whoſe Damnation is Juſt.</hi> And in 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.11, to 15. we are commanded to have no company with ſuch, as through Idleneſs eat not their own Bread, but are buſie Bodies. And 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7, 8. <hi>Purge out therefore the old leaven, that ye may be a new Lump, as ye are unleavened. For even Chriſt our Paſſover is ſacrificed for us. Therefore let us keep the Feaſt, not with old leaven, neither with the leaven of malice and wickedneſs: And</hi> ver. 11. <hi>He ſaith, I have written unto you, not to keep Company, if any man that is called a Brother be a fornicator, or covetous, or an Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>later, or a railer, or a drunkard, or an extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner, with ſuch an one not to eat.</hi> And in <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.19, 20, 21.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See alſo</hi> 1 Cor. 6.9, 10. 1 Tim. 1.9, 10. Col. 3.9.</note> 
               <hi>Now the works of the fleſh are manifeſt, which are theſe, Adultery, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, uneleanneſs, laſeiviouſneſs, idolatry, witchcraft, hatred, variance, emulation, wrath, ſtrife, ſeditions, hereſies, envyings, murders, drunkenneſs, revellings and ſuch like, (as all lyars,</hi> Rev. 21.8.) <hi>of the which I tell you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as I have alſo told you in time paſt, that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50130:4"/>they which do ſuch things, ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God.</hi> And then ſurely none of thoſe evils (tho' of the leſſer ſort of them) when known to us ſhould be ſuffered in the Communion of a Goſpel Church. And in <hi>Math.</hi> 7.12. <hi>Therefore all things whatſoever, ye would that men ſhould do to you, do ye even ſo to them: for this is the Law and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</hi> So that whatſoever wrong is done to any contrary to this general precept, it is a breach of the Moral Law,<note place="margin">Math. 19.19.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf.</hi> And therefore ſuch Offenders ſhould not (without Repentance for their Sin) be ſuffered in our Holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion at the Lords Table.</p>
            <p>But ſome may think that all thoſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular evils, in <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.19, 20, 21. come not under the Cognizance and Judgment of the Church for excluding of thoſe who are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of them from Communion. To which I ſhall briefly ſay, That tho' there may be ſome kind of immoral Variance, Emulation, Wrath and Strife, that may not ariſe to ſo high an offence, if they be only ſuddain paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions that are ſoon over, yet where there is a ſixed <hi>Variance</hi> between Brethren, that ſhews it ſelf to proceed from immorality; Or <hi>Emulation</hi> from a ſtriving to exceed in <hi>Envy,</hi> or <hi>Diſdain,</hi> or in <hi>Wrong</hi> to another; or malicious anger without a cauſe, there we have ground for Excluſion from Communion, as our Saviour ſaith,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.22, to 25.</note> 
               <hi>Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is angry with his Brother without a cauſe, ſhall be in danger of the Judgment. — Therefore
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50130:5"/>if thou bring thy Gift to the altar, and there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membreſt that thy Brother hath ought againſt thee; leave there thy Gift before the altar, and go thy way, firſt be reconciled to thy Brother, and then come and offer thy Gift.</hi> Theſe Words (notwithſtanding there are ſome old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Terms uſed) were ſpoken for Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to us under the Goſpel, for Chriſt in this Sermon was Goſpelizing the Law. And therefore I gather from them, that in Caſe a Perſon treſpaſſeth againſt his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he ſhould not offer his ſpiritual Gift in publick Church Worſhip, till he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled himſelf to him; and then it conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently follows, that the ſame treſpaſs which debars him from offering his Gift up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Altar, whatever is meant by it, does alſo debar him from his full Communion at the Lords Table. And ſeeing from this Scripture, he ought of himſelf to forbear his Communion, till he be reconciled; there is likewiſe Reaſon for the offended Brother or the Church if the Caſe be known to it, to forbear his Communion with him or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw it from him, till he giveth ſatisfaction by Repentance for the ſame immoral Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, which forfeits his preſent Priviledge to Miniſter in publick Church Worſhip, does alſo forfeit his Priviledge of Commuion with it at the Lords Table. Moreover it is worth our Obſervation, that the Word <hi>[There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore] if thou bring thy Gift to the Altar,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers the Reaſon of this Excluſion from Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, to the Evils in the foregoing Verſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50130:5"/>as the cauſe thereof, which is for being <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry</hi> with a Brother without a cauſe, for ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Brother <hi>Raca,</hi> that is, dull, bloc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Dutch Annot.</note> or vain, or thou fool, in diſdain, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and envy. So that as on the one hand we are forbidden on forfeiture of our Church Communion, to caſt contempt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and ſcorn upon any Brother, for his weakneſs in the Faith, or for his natural Infirmities, and to bear a ſixed anger with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a cauſe: So on the other ſide, nothing is here intended by our Saviour, to forbid an intelligible expreſſing of our Deteſtation and Abhorrence of that which is Evil as we are commanded,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.9. 2 Cor. 7.11. Ch. 10.6.</note> and as alſo we are allowed to uſe a holy Indignation and Revenge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all diſobedience, yet ſo as to conſiſt with Love and Pity to Mens Perſons.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Under this Head of Diſeourſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning corrupt Manners or evil Actions, we may bring many other particular Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, for which Offenders ought to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn from, and without Repentance for their Sin, they ſhould not be ſuffered in the Communion of the Viſible Church of Chriſt. As 1. For breaking the Chriſtian Sabbath in diſobedience to the Fourth Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the Example of Chriſts Apoſtles, and the Primitive Churches. 2.<note place="margin">Eph. 6.1, 2, 5.</note> For being diſobedient to Parents and Maſters in Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and Reaſonable things. 3. For a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious breaking Covenant with a Church of Chriſt, when it is not in Caſe of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, of Moral Neceſſity, nor of real Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediency.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50130:6"/>4. For taking the Holy Name of the Lord our God in vain.<note place="margin">Gal. 5.19, 21. 2 Tim. 3.2, to 6.</note> 5. For Laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viouſneſs (mentioned before) which is Lecherouſneſs or Wantonneſs in Behaviour, and for many other Sins, ſome of which are particularly expreſſed, and others are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded under the general Head of Treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes againſt the Moral Law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is the Duty of Chriſtians to withdraw their Communion in Church Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip from all thoſe that hold erroneous Doctrine in or againſt Matters of Faith Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential to Salvation. For</p>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2, 22.</note> We are commanded to <hi>follow Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onſneſs, Faith, Charity, Peace with them that call on the Name of the Lord out of a pure Heart;</hi> but ſuch as Err in fundamentals of Salvation, thereby declare their Hearts to be unwaſhed with Regeneration, and the Renewings of the Holy Ghoſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſhould not hold our Communion with ſuch at the Lords Table.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It farther appears to be the Duty of Chriſtians to ſeparate themſelves from the Communion of all thoſe that hold ſuch Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous Doctrine, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.20. <hi>Wherefore if ye be dead with Chriſt from the Rudiments of the World; why, as tho' living in the World, are ye ſubject to Ordinances. Touch not, taſte not, handle not; (which all are to periſh with the uſing) after the Commandments and Doctrines of Men; which things have indeed a ſhew of Wiſdom in Will-worſhip and Humility, and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting of the Body, not in any Honour, to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50130:6"/>of the Fleſh.</hi> Here I ſhall obſerve, that the Apoſtle having in the foregoing part of this Chapter, warned the <hi>Coloſſians</hi> againſt the Traditions of Men, and the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments of the World, <hi>viz.</hi> to beware of Phyloſophy and vain Deceit of the Jewiſh Ceremonies, and other voluntary Worſhip and Humility; he delivers them a general command, that they ſhould not <hi>Touch, Taſte,</hi> nor <hi>Handle,</hi> viz. no ways to meddle with that which others periſh with the uſing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Commandments and Doctrines of Men, tho' others uſe them; yet we are ſtrictly prohibited in the leaſt to Touch or Taſte of their practical Ordinances, or of their Doctrines, for theſe alſo are there for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden, becauſe the command hath a refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the Rudiments of the World,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 20.</note> which ſignifieth the firſt Teaching or Inſtruction, a beginning a Principle, and hath reſpect to Matters of Faith.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 3. to 10.</note> Seeing therefore we are forbidden to Touch, Taſte or Handle the Commandments and Doctrines of Men; then ſurely we ought not to be in full Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion at the Lords Table, with Perſons that hold ſuch Erroneous Principles; for our Aſſenting to their right of Communion with us, is an owning their Principles as truly fundamental to Salvation; and ſo we either virtually deny our own to be ſuch, or confound the true Profeſſion of our Faith to the hazard of Mens Souls; or elſe admit of Perſons to partake of the Holy Supper, that apparently have no right to it, for want of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50130:7"/>thoſe Goſpel Principles that are eſſential to their viſible Intereſt, in the Obedience, Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, and Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt, either of which is a Sin.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It appears from <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.6, 7, 8. that we ſhould not hold Communion at the Lords Table, with Perſons that hold ſuch errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Principles; for the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>I mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, that ye are ſo ſoon removed from him that called you into the Grace of Chriſt, unto another Goſpel: Which is not another, but there be ſome that trouble you, and would pervert the Goſpel of Chriſt. But tho' we, or an Angel from Heaven, preach any other Goſpel unto you, than that which we have preached unto you, let him be accurſed:</hi> And in the following Verſe, he repeats it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver again; and in <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.12. he ſaith, <hi>I would they were even cut off which trouble you.</hi> Now if we duly ſearch after the Cauſe of this cenſure, we may plainly ſee that it was not for bringing in of another Goſpel; but as the Apoſtle ſaith, becauſe there were ſome that troubled the Church of <hi>Galatia</hi> with perverting the.<note place="margin">Gal. 6.12. <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.3.</note> Goſpel of Chriſt, by conſtraining them to be circumciſed; and ſo to become Debtors to do the whole Law. And we find by the Apoſtles Diſcourſe, that they ſought to be juſtified by the Works of the Law,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 2, &amp;c.</note> as <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.16. <hi>Knowing that a man is not juſtified by the Works of the Law, but by the Faith of Jeſus Chriſt, even we have believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Jeſus Chriſt; that we might be juſtified by the Faith of Chriſt, and not by the Works of the Law: for by the Works of the Law ſhall no
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50130:7"/>Fleſh be juſtified.</hi> And <hi>Chap.</hi> 4.21. <hi>Tell me, ye that deſire to be under the Law, do ye not hear the Law?</hi> So that the pervert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Goſpel before mentioned, was by bringing in of the Works of the Law for Juſtification; and this we find was made a Matter of Separation, the Apoſtle wiſhing the Perſons even cut off or accurſed, that ſo troubled the Church of Chriſt, which to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to ſome in our preſent day, I ſhall here note, that altho' thoſe Jewiſh Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans that held it needful to be circumciſed, and ſo endeavoured to bring the <hi>Gentiles</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law for Juſtification to Eternal Life, did it in a Mcſaical formal way, which Chriſtians now repugn, by denying that formal Obligation to keep the old Law; yet as their Principles oblige them to ſeek for Juſtification by works of Obedience to a new Law under the Goſpel, which they have no Power in themſelves to perform, their Principle with the caſe of the Church of <hi>Galatia,</hi> reſpecting the effect, is in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance the ſame; and therefore there is Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon founded on Scripture for us to withdraw or remove our Communion from all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that are leavened with the works of the Law for Juſtification; whether it be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the form of the Law or of the Goſpel Adminiſtration:<note place="margin">Gal. 5.9. 1 Cor. 5.8.</note> For that being called Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſeeing <hi>Chriſt our Paſſover is ſacrificed for us,</hi> we are commanded (tho' on a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent occaſion) to <hi>keep the Feaſt not with old leaven, neither with the leaven of malice and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50130:8"/>wickedneſs; but with the unleavened Bread of of Sincerity and Truth.</hi> Obſerve it well, we are here forbidden to eat the Chriſtian Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſover or Lords Supper with the old leaven, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and are commanded to keep it with <hi>Truth.</hi> And therefore we ſhould not have Communion in that Ordinance with funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Errors in the Chriſtian Faith.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17. <hi>Now I beſeech you, Brethren, Mark them which cauſe Diviſions and Offences, contrary to the Doctrine which ye have Learned; and avoid them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.3, 4, 5.</note> And <hi>Paul</hi> commanded <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> to withdraw from ſuch as taught other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and conſented not to wholſome Words, even the Words of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; and to the Doctrine which is according to Godlineſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And we are exhorted <hi>ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly to contend for the Faith which was once delivered unto the Saints:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jude 3. Phil. 1.27.</note> And to <hi>ſtand faſt in one Spirit, with one Mind, ſtriving together for the Faith of the Goſpel;</hi> and therefore we are not to unite our ſelves into one Body with Perſons, that erre from the true Faith; for as two cannot walk together except they be agreed,<note place="margin">Amos 3.3.</note> ſo if we are not united in one Faith, we ſhall quickly be contending and ſtriving with each other, and not together for the Faith of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It is ſaid by way of Politive Command, <hi>A Man that is an Heretick,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 3.10, 11.</note> 
               <hi>after the firſt and ſecond Admonition, reject: Knowing that he that is ſuch, is ſubverted, and ſinneth, being condemned of himſelf.</hi> Now an Heritick is
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50130:8"/>one that ſtiſly maintains falſe opinions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Scriptures, in matters of Faith fundamental to Salvation; which tho' we ſhould be tender of judging ſuch Chriſtians to be Hereticks, as there is Reaſon to hope have more the ſhew in weak expreſſions of ſome ſuch like ſalſe Principles, than a being under the Power and Conduct of them; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scripture ſaith,<note place="margin">Jude 22.</note> we ſhould <hi>of ſome have Compaſſion, making a difference; and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſave with fear pulling them out of the Fire, hating even the garment ſpotted by the Fleſh.</hi> Yet our Charitable Thoughts of ſuch Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, while they are under their cloudy Profeſſion of ſuch Errours (tho' crouded amongſt other Truths, whereby they are the more concealed) are no warrant nor allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance for us to hold Communion with them, till we can plainly ſee them delivered from thoſe Errours, ſeeing they are clearly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited in the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It is the Duty of Chriſtians to withdraw their Communion from all diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly Perſons in falſe Worſhip, or in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Adminiſtrations of Goſpel-Ordinances. And</p>
            <p n="1">1. Our Lord ſaith, <hi>The hour cometh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 4.23, 24.</note> 
               <hi>and now is, when the true Worſhippers ſhall worſhip the Father in Spirit and in Truth: For the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeeketh ſuch to worſhip him. God is a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and they that worſhip him muſt worſhip him in Spirit and in Truth.</hi> From hence I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that true Worſhippers muſt worſhip the Father both in Spirit and in Truth, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50130:9"/>therwiſe they are not true Worſhippers: And then if we find by the Word of Truth (as we are commanded to try the Spirits, whither they are of God) that they are ſuch <hi>who ſeparate themſelves,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 4.1. Jude 19.</note> 
               <hi>ſenſual, having not the Spirit,</hi> or that do not worſhip in Truth, but with erroneous Matter, or in a falſe Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: I ſay, then we ſhould withdraw our Communion from ſuch, as diſorderly Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in Divine Worſhip:<note place="margin">Mat. 15.9.</note> And our Lord al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo tells us, that in vain they do worſhip him, teaching for Doctrines the Commandments of Men. So that to keep our ſelves from the Guilt of vain Worſhip, we ſhould not by our ſelves,<note place="margin">Iſa. 29.19.</note> nor with any others worſhip God after the Commandment of Men, but according to Goſpel-Inſtitutions.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Apoſtle ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. <hi>I praiſe you, Brethren, that you remember me in all things, and keep the Ordinances, as I deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered them to you:</hi> On this Text Mr. <hi>Will. Kiſſin</hi> noteth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See his Book called</hi> A Sober Diſcourſe of right to Church-Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in his Preſace.</note> 
               <q>That our Tranſlation of the Greek Word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (rendring it <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances</hi>) is excepted againſt by ſome Papiſts — who would have it tranſlated <hi>(Traditions)</hi> to countenance the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Opinion; to which (ſaith he) ſhall be oppoſed, that the Greek Word ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth indeed <hi>Tradition,</hi> that is in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> a Delivery, <hi>viz.</hi> of Doctrines, Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Inſtructions, or Inſtitutions, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.15. by thoſe Evangelical Preachers to their Auditors, which is nothing elſe but the Doctrine of the Goſpel firſt preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50130:9"/>and afterwards committed to writing by the Evangeliſts and Apoſtles, as ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Records to future Ages ſo that any Traditions, beſides what is written, are juſtly to be excepted againſt, and (in matters relating to Divine Worſhip) to be eſteemed Apocryphal.</q> Now as the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Author ſaith, <q>What was praiſe-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy in thoſe <hi>Primitive</hi> Chriſtians, to whom the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> writes, — can be no blemiſh, but really a Duty in other Chriſtians in after times, to imitate.</q> To which I add, That to corrupt the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God with mens Traditions, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Apoſtolical Pattern, is a Sin and Diſorder to be purged out by the Church of Chriſt; as farther appears in the next Section.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It's ſaid, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Now we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you, Brethren, in the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that ye withdraw your ſelves from every Brother that walketh diſorderly, and not after the Tradition which he received of us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. This general Command to the Church of the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> appears from the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Verſes, to be occaſioned from ſome particular diſorders that were amongſt them, (as <hi>Ver.</hi> 11, 12, 14, 15. <hi>For even when we were with you, this we commanded you, that if any would not work, neither ſhould he eat. For we hear that there are ſome which walk among you diſorderly, working not at all, but are buſie bodies. Now them that are ſuch we command, and exhort by our Lord Jeſus
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50130:10"/>Chriſt, that with quietneſs they work, and eat their own Bread. — And if any Man obey not our Word by this Epiſtle, note that Man, and have no Company with him, that he may be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. Yet count him not as an Enemy, but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh him as a Brother.)</hi> But yet this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance leſt us on ſacred Record, may give us light into other Caſes; for ſeeing we are commanded to withdraw our Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, ſo as to have no Company with ſuch a diſorderly Brother, that through Idleneſs (when he may have work) eateth not his own Bread, and is a buſie body (who may have this to plead againſt ſuch an Act of the Church, that he hath not ſtolen nor defrauded any, but getteth his Meat from Houſe to: Houſe amongſt his Chriſtian Friends) then there is ground and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand for us to withdraw our ſelves from all thoſe that offend in other things of the like Nature, and that are guilty of frand or deceit and wrong to any Perſon. And that this command in <hi>Ver.</hi> 6. is general, including all diſorders in Manners, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and falſe Worſhip, and ſo is a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of all I have ſaid before for proof thereof, appears as followeth.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe in <hi>Ver.</hi> 7, 8. there is a plain Intimation, that the command, <hi>Ver.</hi> 6. <hi>To withdraw from every Brother that walketh diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly,</hi> does reſpect other diſorders beſides the particular Caſe of eating other Mens Bread for nought. For the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Ver.</hi> 7, 8. <hi>Your ſelves know how ye ought to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:50130:10"/>us: for we behaved not our ſelves diſorderly among you, neither did we eat any Mans Bread for nought.</hi> Obſerve the Word <hi>[Neither]</hi> imports a different diſorder to what he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed before in Oppoſition to his Example: So that to me it's plain, that the command in the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, was to withdraw from thoſe diſorders that were contrary to the Apoſtles examples, and which were not after the Tradition which they received of them, and therefore it is a general command, as was ſaid before.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I ſhall give a brief Citation, of what is ſaid on the ſame Text in a Book intitled, <hi>Aſober Diſcourſe of Right to Church Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> in <hi>Page</hi> 5. it's ſaid,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Written by Mr.</hi> Will. Kiffin.</note> quoting 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Now we command you Brethren, in the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that ye with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw your ſelves from every Brother that walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth diſorderly, and not after the Tradition which he received of us.</hi> 
               <q>Which laſt Phraſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (the Word <hi>[Paradoſis]</hi> ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not only Doctrine delivered, <hi>Math.</hi> 15.2, 3. but alſo a Command, Ordinance or Inſtitution, as before, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.15.) plainly makes out, that they were not only to withdraw from Perſons of diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly Converſation, or defective in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, but alſo from ſuch as were corrupt in Doctrine, or diſorderly in their Goſpel Adminiſtrations, that being as great a Violation of Goſpel Order, and as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitious to Chriſtians as Immorality: Which muſt be granted, or elſe there
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:50130:11"/>is no Authority given to the Church to deal with Members of corrupt Principles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Now this Command (ſaith he) being general, includes all diſorders of any kind, in Manners, Doctrine, or Practice, and is a ſufficient warrant (were there no more) for our Obedience, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude ſuch as diſorderly practiſe the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of Baptiſm, from our immediate Communion at the Lords Table, tho' not from our Love and Affections.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Having hitherto been diſcovering the Scripture Grounds of Separation from Church Communion with all diſorderly Perſons, in Manners, Doctrine, falſe Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip or irregular Adminiſtrations of Goſpel Ordinances, I ſhall now proceed as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth:
<list>
                  <item>1. To Anſwer the chiefeſt Objections I find againſt ſuch Goſpel Separation.</item>
                  <item>2. To give a particular Inſtance of ſome confuſed Matter about Communion, alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Printed amongſt us with ſeveral Queries thereupon.</item>
                  <item>3. I ſhall preſent my humble Advice to ſome of our Baptized Churches. And</item>
                  <item>4. I ſhall leave ſome few things to the ſerious Conſideration of thoſe that have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a Gracious Diſcovery of the Love and Favour of God unto their Souls, or that have good Hope thro' Grace of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life; and yet are walking at large out of the Communion of a Goſpel Church: As
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:50130:11"/>alſo an Exhortation in another Caſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Goſpel Communion.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly in a Poſtſcript, I have ſhewed, that it is the Duty of all true Believers in Order to Church Communion, to ſubject themſelves to the Ordinance of Water Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, and have alſo diſcourſed againſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of apparel, and then made a general Concluſion of this Treatiſe.</p>
            <div type="objections_and_answers">
               <head>Objections Anſwered.</head>
               <p n="1">I. <hi>Object.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.</note> None of the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> in the Epiſtles, to them were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to withdraw their Communion, or ſeparate themſelves from any of thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons among them, which the Holy Ghoſt charged with Evil. And therefore neither Churches from any of their Members, nor any Members from their Churches, ſhould ſeparate themſelves from one anothers full Communion at the Lords Table, unleſs it be for groſs and ſcandalous Evils.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer:</hi> If this Argument holdeth good and warrantable for Perſons and Churches to keep their Communion at the Lords Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, under the Guilt and Non-repentance of leſſer Evils; it will alſo juſtifie ſuch Communion with thoſe that are guilty of groſſer Sins. For the Church of <hi>Pergamos</hi> had them that held <hi>the Doctrine of Balaam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ch. 2.14.</note> 
                  <hi>who taught Balak to caſt a ſtumbling block be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Children of Iſrael, to eat things ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed unto Idols, and to commit Fornication.</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:50130:12"/>And this was alſo the Sin of the Church in <hi>Thyatira,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ver.</hi> 24, 25.</note> to whom its ſaid, <hi>That unto the reſt in Thyatira, as many as have not this Doctrine, and which have not known the depths of Stan, as they ſpeak, I will put upon you none other burthen. But that which you have already hold faſt till I come.</hi> And therefore, ſeeing the Church of <hi>Thyratira</hi> ſuffered that Woman <hi>Jezebel</hi> to ſeduce the Servants of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ver.</hi> 20.</note> to commit Fornication, and to eat things ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed to Idols (which muſt be meant in honour to them,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 8.9, 10. Ch. 10.27, 28, 29.</note> for otherwiſe Meats ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed to Idols were not unlawful to eat, tho' ſometimes not expedient for the ſake of weak Brethren) then ſurely the reſt that eſcaped thoſe Pollutions, and had no other burthen put upon them, than to hold faſt that they had already, cannot rationally be thought then to be in the ſame Communion with thoſe Idolaters and Fornicators,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.19, 20, 21.</note> for ſuch have no Inheritance in the Kingdom of God.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.2, 4, 5.</note> Beſides, we have an Inſtance of a Fornicator that was ſeparated from the Church, or delivered up unto Satan. So that tho' there is no expreſs command in the Epiſtles to thoſe ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> for withdrawing their Communion from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny evils mentioned therein; yet doubtleſs it was their Duty from other Precepts then written, to caſt out thoſe that were guilty of ſuch notorious Sins, as were in ſome of thoſe Churches: And thoſe Chriſtians of <hi>Thyatira,</hi> which the Holy Ghoſt commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that were in the ſame City with thoſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:50130:12"/>that were reproved (and perhaps originally in full Communion together in one Body) it is rational to believe were ſeparated from their Communion, for Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> in his Margin reads in <hi>Ver.</hi> 24. thus: But un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>[you, I ſay the reſt]</hi> in <hi>Thyatira,</hi> &amp;c. for the Kings, <hi>M. S.</hi> reads it ſo<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>See alſo the Bibles Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Deputies of</hi> Chriſ. Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, 1599. <hi>and by</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, 1607. Ch. 2.2.</note> , which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports another diſtinct Church or People in that City. And the Reaſon why Chriſt threatned thoſe defiled Chriſtians, which were the Church to whom the Epiſtle was primarily directed, was becauſe they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered thoſe evils, when they ſhould have purged out ſuch Offenders, as the Church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> did, for what elſe can be meant by thoſe Words: <hi>I know thy Works — how thou canſt not bear them which are Evil: and thou haſt tried them, which ſay they are Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and are not; and haſt found them liars,</hi> who were therefore doubtleſs rejected from their Communion. But if any ſay, that theſe Words, <hi>thou canſt not bear them which are evil,</hi> have only reſpect to the following Words. <hi>And thou haſt tryed them, which ſay they are Apoſtles, and are not; and haſt found them lyars:</hi> I have this to Anſwer, 1. That if it were ſo, yet it ſhews that this Church did not bear with ſuch Lyars in their Communion, otherwiſe they could not be properly commended for not bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with them. 2. The Word <hi>[and] thou haſt tryed them,</hi> &amp;c. implieth a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular different thing, or other Perſons to thoſe preceding Words in general: <hi>And
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:50130:13"/>how thou canſt not bear them which are evil;</hi> like as we find in the ſame Verſe, that the Word <hi>[and] thy Labour, [and] thy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,</hi> denoteth different things to each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and particulars of the general Word <hi>(I know thy) [Works.]</hi> So that the Text does clearly demonſtrate, that the Church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> did neither bear thoſe that were Evil, nor thoſe falſe Apoſtles in their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, which Expoſition is confirmed by the <hi>Dutch</hi> Annotations on thoſe Words, <hi>and how thou canſt not bear them which are evil,</hi> that is, ſay they, <hi>ſuch as are ſcandalous in Life and Doctrine. Thus their Zealis commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded here in the Everciſe of Eccleſiaſtical Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline.</hi> So that the aforeſaid Objection, That none of the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> were commanded in their Epiſtles to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate themſelves from any of thoſe Perſons, which the Holy Ghoſt charged with evil, is invalid. And conſidering alſo, that his ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence may be improved (if we give ear to ſuch a groundleſs Argument) for holding Communion with groſſer as well as leſſer Sins; we have Reaſon to believe, that ſome of thoſe Churches and Chriſtians, that were concerned in thoſe Epiſtles (from the Authority of ſome other part of the Holy Scriptures) did ſeparate themſelves from thoſe offenders, that by the Laws of Chriſt they were not to bear in their Communion. And that thoſe Churches, who ſuffered themſelves to be polluted, through the neglect of their Duty in bearing with thoſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:50130:13"/>evils they ſhould have purged out, did thereby bring themſelves under the anger and diſpleaſure of God for it, as appears in their Epiſtles.</p>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>Object.</hi> Is from <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.15, 16. <hi>Let us therefore, as many as be perfect, be thus mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: and if in any thing ye be otherwiſe minded, God ſhall reveal even this unto you. Nevertheleſs, whereto we have already attained, let us walk by the ſame Rule, let us mind the ſame Thing.</hi> That theſe Words give no allowance for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to hold a corrupt Communion, is very plain, becauſe the Apoſtle is not here argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to prove the Reſurrection of the Dead, or any fundamental Article of our Faith, or on any eſſential part of Divine Worſhip, or of ſuch practical Obedience, as that the failure thereof is to be noted as diſorderly walking: But he is Treating in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding Verſes, that he had not attained, but was following after the Reſurrection-ſtate of Perfection, and of his preſſing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Mark, for the Prize of the high Calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus; and then it follows, <hi>Let us therefore, as many as be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, be thus minded: and if in any thing ye be otherwiſe minded, God ſhall reveal even this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you.</hi> As if he ſhould fay, Let us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as many as be <hi>[perfect]</hi> that is,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.1. 1 Joh. 2.14. Heb. 5.12, 13, 14. 1 Cor. 2.6.</note> as are not <hi>[babes]</hi> in Chriſt, that have need of <hi>[Milk]</hi> but are <hi>[ſtrong Men]</hi> of <hi>[full Age] [skilful]</hi> in the Word of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, <hi>who by Reaſon of uſe have their Senſes exerciſed to diſcern both good and evil. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.17. Col. 4.12. Jam. 3.2. Eph. 3.18, 19.</note>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:50130:14"/>
                  <hi>throughly ſurniſhed unto all good Works. Perfect and compleat in all the Will of God. To be able to comprehend with all Saints, what is the breadth, and length, and depth, and heighth; and to know the Love of Chriſt, which paſſeth Knowledge, that ye might be filled with all the fulneſs of God.</hi> Now conſider, that as we cannot know that which paſſeth Knowledge, but as the Apoſtle ſaith, we know in part,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.12.</note> and as none but Chriſt was ever filled with all the fulneſs of the Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of God; but of the Knowledge of his Will, and Love to us in all its parts ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to a Holy Life of Faith, the true Worſhip of God and Eternal Life: So if any came ſhort of this kind of Perfection, the Apoſtle told them, God ſhould reveal even this unto them. And therefore the Text does not any ways prohibit a Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from ſuch aforeſaid Errours, that are noted in Holy Writ, as diſorders in Manners, Doctrine or Worſhip. But it containeth a comfortable Promiſe to thoſe that are rather free from them; that tho' they are weak in Faith, and Babes in the Knowledge of Chriſt, yet ſincerely mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſome things which according to Rule they have attained to, and labouring to grow in Grace,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.18.</note> and in the Knowledge of Chriſt, they ſhall have in due Seaſon a more full diſcovery of that perfect Love,<note place="margin">1 Joh. 4.12, 18.</note> which caſteth out fear, and of the Will of God in the Revelation of the Goſpel, and ſhall be built up in their moſt Holy Faith
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:50130:14"/>from a babe-like-ſtate to a perfect Man in Chriſt Jeſus, in ſome Scripture Senſe. So that there is nothing in the Text, that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plieth a Prohibition of Separation in the aforeſaid Caſes of corrupt Manners, Erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous, Doctrine, falſe Worſhip, or irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Adminiſtrations of Goſpel Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
               <p n="3">III. <hi>Object.</hi> Is from, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.8. and <hi>Math.</hi> 18.21, 22. <hi>And above all things have fervent Charity among your ſelves: for Charity ſhall cover a Multitude of Sins.</hi> And <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid, <hi>Lord, How oft ſhall my Brother Sin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me; and I forgive him? till ſeven times? Jeſus ſaid unto him, I ſay not unto thee; until ſeven times: but, until ſeventy times ſeven;</hi> from which Scriptures, ſome may think that Chriſtians ſhould bear with Sins in Communion with one another, and cover them all in Love.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer,</hi> Our Lord himſelf ſhews plainly us, what is meant by thoſe Scriptures, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.3. <hi>Take heed to your ſelves: If thy Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther treſpaſs againſt thee, rebuke him; and if he repent, forgive him. And if he treſpaſs againſt thee ſeven times in a day, and ſeven times in a day turn again to thee, ſaying, I repent, thou ſhalt forgive him.</hi> From whence it appears, 1. That we are to rebuke our Brother for his Treſpaſs. 2. To forgive him, but mind it well, it muſt be if he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn and repenteth; he muſt turn again as well as ſay he repenteth; and ſo tho' Charity ſhould cover a multitude of Sins,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:50130:15"/>that are turned from and repented of, yet it ſhould cover none from the Church which ought to come under her Cognizance, for our Charity ſhould conſiſt with our Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Procepts of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. <hi>Object.</hi> It is ſaid, <hi>Rebuke not an Elder,</hi> and therefore there ſhould be a difference between dealing with an Elder of a Church and a private Member, for Sin.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.12.</note> The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in this Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Let no Man deſpiſe thy Youth.</hi> And in <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.1, 2. he exhorteth him ſaying, <hi>Rebuke not an Elder, but intreat him as a Father, and the younger Men as Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; the Elder Women as Mothers, the younger as Siſters with all Purity.</hi> And <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.14, 15. <hi>Theſe things write I unto thee, — that thou mayeſt know how thou oughteſt to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have thy ſelf in the Houſe of God.</hi> In theſe Scriptures the Apoſtle inſtructed <hi>Timothy,</hi> that young Servant of Chriſt, and in him others, how they ſhould behave themſelves, in reproving not only Elders, but younger Brethren and Siſters; that as an Elder Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop or Paſtour, which is the ſame in Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,<note place="margin">Tir. 1.7.</note> ſhould not be <hi>[ſoon angry]</hi> ſo <hi>Timothy,</hi> and others ſhould not in an angry Spirit, rebuke either Elders or younger Brethren and Siſters, but rather reprove them by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaties. It's true, it's alſo ſaid, <hi>Let the Elders that Rule well, be counted worthy of dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Honour:</hi> But yet by Sin, they may loſe and juſtly forfeit their double and ſingle Honour too;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ver.</hi> 19.20, 21.</note> for its ſaid, <hi>Againſt an Elder
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:50130:15"/>receive not an. Accuſation, but before</hi> (or as it is in our Margin <hi>under</hi>) <hi>two or three wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes. Them that Sin rebuke before all, that others alſo may fear: I charge thee before God and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the Elect An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, that thou obſerve theſe things without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring one before another, doing nothing by par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality.</hi> So that it ſeems to be implyed, that the Chriſtians in thoſe Primitive times were ſo zealous to preſerve the Reputation of the Goſpel-Miniſtry, and the Purity of their Communion; as that they were ready to receive an Accuſation againſt an Elder ſooner, and on leſſer evidence than againſt a private Member; inſomuch as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle thought it needful, to charge them not to receive an Accuſation againſt an Elder, under the legal Evidence of two or three Witneſſes. Moreover, we ſee how ſtrictly the Apoſtle charged <hi>Timothy,</hi> that he ſhould not uſe partiality in any Caſe of Sin, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer one before another, whether Elders (as there were ſometimes ſeveral in one Church) or private Members;<note place="margin">Tit. 1.5. Act. 20.17. Gal. 2.11, 14.</note> but them that ſinned ſhould be rebuked before all, <hi>i. e.</hi> thoſe whoſe Sins could not be privately covered for want of their Repentance, they who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they were ſhould be rebuked before all, <hi>viz.</hi> ſo as the rebuke ſhould reach as openly as the Sins were known, and that others might alſo fear. And therefore, there is not the leaſt Reaſon from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for any to imagine that an Elders Sin ſhould be more favourably dealt with
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:50130:16"/>than a private Members, or that there is a different Rule for judging of them; but that the Precepts of Chriſt for purging out the Leaven of Unrighteouſneſs, are to all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like;<note place="margin">Eph. 6.9. Col. 3.25. Lev. 10.1, 2. Deut. 1.17.</note> for as the Lord reſpecteth no Mans Perſon, no not for Office-ſake: So he hath commanded us, ſaying, Ye ſhall not reſpect Perſons in Judgment.</p>
               <p n="5">V. <hi>Object.</hi> We ought not to leave a Church, till Chriſt be departed from it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer</hi> 1. If this be true, then no Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed Congregation ſhould receive a Member from our Brethrens Communion of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependant Churches: For who can ſay that Chriſt hath left them, ſo as not to ſucceed their Miniſtry with true Converſion of Souls, and ſo as not to give ſomething of his gracious preſence to them and others, that are ſound in the fundamental Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to Salvation; who truly fear the Lord and ſincerely obey him according to their Light, tho' the Miſt of Mens Traditions may not be clearly wiped from off their Eyes. I think none can be ſo uncharitable and cenſorious as to affirm it: But yet we may ſafely ſay, the more we come up in our Obedience to the perfect Rule of Chriſt, the greater our Peace and Comfort ſhall be, and the more or the preſence of God, we ſhall enjoy in the gracious diſcoveries of his Eternal Love unto our Souls.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If Chriſt hath not left our aforeſaid Brethren (and others that are not of our Communion) without ſome gracious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtations
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:50130:16"/>of his Preſence among them. And if therefore, according to the Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, their Members ought not to leave their Churches, do not then thoſe <hi>Baptiſts</hi> which plead this Argument for a mixed Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion among themſelves, and yet receive the Members of thoſe Independant Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, condemn themſelves thereby; as Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenancers, Abetters and Receivers of diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly Perſons, and as ſuch, who according to this Objection, have little or nothing more to ſay for their Separation, and keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up a diſtinct Church-ſtate from them, then for a private and worldly Intereſt. And therefore away with ſuch Pretenſions for they are but a ſhame to us.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If we ought not to leave a Church, 'till Chriſt is departed from it, it muſt be meant, either of a partial or total depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: If it be underſtood of Chriſt's Partial departing from a Church, we muſt either allow it lawful for a Member to leave his preſent Communion, when Chriſt hath in part forſaken that Church, ſo as for their Declenſion of Spirit they are ſuffered to fall into ſuch corrupt Manners, erroneous Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, falſe Worſhip, or irregular Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which the Lord hath commanded to be purged out from among them; or elſe that the Church it ſelf has Power to preſcribe Limits of Communion, according as ſhe ſhall judge, (without regard to the written Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of Chriſt) that his preſence doth bound it. But as I believe, no Baptized Churches will
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:50130:17"/>open their Mouths in favour of ſuch an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Authority within themſelves, for that we own the Scriptures to be our Rule; ſo it cannot be denied, but that it is lawful for Members to remove their Communion to a Church which is more Pure, for the ſame cauſes; as a Church ſhould withdraw their Communion from a ſingle Member, if for any cauſe at all. But if they mean, that we ſhould not ſeparate from a Church, till Chriſt is wholly departed from it; then it may be alſo argued, that a Church ſhould not withdraw their Communion from a Member, till Chriſt be wholly departed from him. Beſides, if a ſingle Member ſhould not depart from a Church, till Chriſt be wholly departed from it, then the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is, Whether Chriſt may be ſaid total<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to depart from a Church, till at leaſt it is manifeſt, that ſhe is abſolutely apoſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in her Spirit from ſome one Article of our Chriſtian Faith, which is eſſential to Salvation; and if till then it be unlawful for ſingle Perſons to ſeparate their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion from a Church of Chriſt, than if their Church worſhippeth God in a falſe manner, ſo it be not in fundamentals of Salvation, and maketh void a Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God through Mens Traditions, and are corrupted in their Morals, they muſt ſtill hold their Communion with ſuch a People; and it's hard to tell how far a Church may be guilty of theſe Evils, and not looſe the Eſſentials to Salvation. But
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:50130:17"/>if ſuch a corrupt Communion ought to be held, rather than a Perſons Separation from it ſhould be allowed lawful, the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents of it naturally tends to the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw and Extirpation of our Baptized Churches; for then what Obligation of Conſcience is there for Baptized Believers to ſet up by themſelves ſuch a Church-ſtate, which is deſpiſed and rendred obnoxious to many Chriſtians, and which is accompanied with divers diſcouragements and outward diſadvantages more than others. Beſides, unleſs it be lawful for a Member, or the ſmaller number of a Church, to ſeparate from their corrupt Communion, many Chriſtians cannot reform nor worſhip God with the Church, or in the Adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all Goſpel-Ordinances, according to their Conſciences; for generally Reformers are the feweſt number, and if theſe ſhould continue in their irregular Communion, their Light will be hid and ſmoothered in the croud of corrupt Profeſſors, and rather put under a Buſhel than on a Goſpel Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſtick,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.14, 15, 16.</note> to ſhine more clearly to thoſe that are round about them.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. <hi>Object.</hi> We are (ſay ſome Perſons) for Charity and Union, and therefore we are for Communion at the Lord's Table with Chriſtians, as ſuch: If we believe them to be but real Chriſtians, we ought to hold our Communion with them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer</hi> 1. To our Brethren of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregational or Independant Churches of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:50130:18"/>whom ſome have argued with me after the Nature of this Objection, as if we were too ſtrait in our Charity, for not holding Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with them. To whom I have this to ſay: 1. That I think we may fairly ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from what they have publiſhed (with their Confeſſion of Faith) of the Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Order of Churches, that they do not admit any unbaptized Chriſtians to their Communion at the Lord's Table, for in Article the ſeventh, ſpeaking of <hi>a particular Church gathered and compleated according to the Mind of Chriſt.</hi> In Article the eighth, they ſay, <q>The Members of thoſe Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es are Saints by Calling, viſibly manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and evidencing — their Obedience unto that call of Chriſt, who being fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther known to each other by their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Faith, wrought in them by the Power of God — do willingly Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to walk together, according to the appointment of Chriſt, giving up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Lord, and to one another, by the Will of God, in profeſſed Subjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Ordinances of the Goſpel.</q> So then, if the Members of a compleat Church do willingly conſent to walk together in profeſſed Subjection to the Ordinances of the Goſpel, none that do not ſubject them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Ordinance of Baptiſm in their Sence can be orderly admitted by them, as compleatly quallified to their full Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; and ſo if they will not hold Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with ſuch unbaptized Perſons, they do
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:50130:18"/>not hold it, as ſome of them pretend, with Chriſtians meerly as ſuch; but only with ſuch Chriſtians, which are qualified with Water-Baptiſm to receive the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
               <p>But 2. If they own, that our baptizing Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons on Confeſſion of Faith, by way of dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, is alſo right Baptiſm according to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-Rule: and ſo for this Reaſon, they can freely hold their Communion with us. Yet this is no Corrector, that their Charity is more univerſal then ours, becauſe then they receive us not meerly on the account of their Charity, but as Chriſtians ſitly qualified with Water-Baptiſm. But the Caſe is dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, reſpecting us, for ſeeing we deny their Infant-ſprinkling to be true Baptiſm, or to be of God; and ſo they being to us as unbaptized Perſons; our having ſull Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with them, would be not only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Light of our own Conſciences, but witneſſed againſt by their practice of ſprinkling for Baptiſm, as a qualification to full Communion. And therefore, we have equal Reaſon to ſay, that our refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Church-Communion with them, is not for want of Charity towards them as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, any more then it is for want of it in themſelves to other Chriſtians, that are not ſprinkled or any ways baptized; if they refuſe Communion with them, as ſome have done in their private Conference, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what is gathered as their Mind in Print before. So that I ſee no Reaſon,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:50130:19"/>why our Brethren ſhould in the leaſt be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at us, for keeping our ſelves from their Communion, when otherwiſe, ſo far as I can perceive, their Practice, as well as our own Conſciences would condemn us for ſo doing.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Our aforeſaid Brethren of the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant Churches (however ſome of their Members have in their private Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe reflected on us) have fairly granted,<note place="margin">See their <hi>28</hi> Article of the Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of Churches at the end of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gational Confeſſion of Faith.</note> that a Perſon where he cannot continue in any Church without his Sin, may depart from the Communion of one Church to another. For they ſay, <q>Perſons that are joined in Church-fellowſhip, ought not lightly or without juſt cauſe to withdraw themſelves from the Communion of the Church whereunto they are ſo joined: Nevertheleſs, where any Perſon cannot continue in any Church without his Sin, either for want of the Adminiſtration of any Ordinances inſtituted by Chriſt, or by his being deprived of his due Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, or compelled to any thing in Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice not warranted by the Word, or in caſe of Perſecution, or upon the account of Conveniency of Habitation, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting with the Church, or the Officer, or Officers thereof, may peaceably de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the Communion of the Church wherewith he hath ſo walked, to join himſelf with ſome other Church, where he may enjoy the Ordinances in the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the ſame, for his Edification and Conſolation.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:50130:19"/>
               <p>Now ſeeing they grant, that we may leave our Communion with a Church, to join our ſelves with ſome other Church, where we may enjoy the Ordinances in the Purity of the ſame; then none of them ought to blame us, for not holding our full Communion with them; as if they were the ſtandard of Truth, who we believe are not in the compleat Order and true Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of all Goſpel Ordinances. See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we walk by their Rule of Communion according to our Conſciences, tho' we have not the ſame Light to walk with them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For any of our Baptized Brethren to plead for mixed Communion, from the Obligation of univerſal Charity, for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians as they are ſuch, does rather betray their want of real Love;<note place="margin">Gal. 5.22. 1 Joh. 4.19.</note> for that is a Fruit of the Holy Spirit, flowing firſt from the Faith we have in the Love of God to us; which is the cauſe of Love in us to him,<note place="margin">1 Joh. 5.1.</note> and ſo to our Brethren which are begotten of him; and then our univerſal Love to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians depending on our Love to God, it muſt conſiſt with ſincere Obedience to his Will, ſo far as we are inlightned. <hi>For this is the Love of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 14.21, 23. 1 Joh. 5.2, 3.</note> 
                  <hi>that we keep his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and his Commandments are not grievous. And by this we know that we Love the Children of God, when we Love God and keep his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments.</hi> And therefore, whatſoever Love is pretended, which is inconſiſtent with ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Obedience to Chriſt, 'tis rather to be ſuſpected than counted real. But in Charity I
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:50130:20"/>muſt conclude, it is not for want of Love to the Inſtitutions of Chriſt, but for want of Light that you plead for Communion at the Lords Table with unbaptized Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. However you do thereby virtually de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny your own Baptiſm to be eſſentially ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to a regular Goſpel-Church, and make void that Holy Ordinance of Chriſt, which in Obedience to him you have ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to. Beſides, why may you not then al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſay, that you ought in Charity to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, meerly as ſuch, (altho' they be not yet baptized,) to call any gifted Chriſtian to adminiſter the Ordinances of Preaching, Prayer, and breaking Bread in the Church; and in Charity to thoſe Members that walk diſorderly, and break the Commandments of Chriſt, forbear the Execution of his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of withdrawing your Church-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion from them, becauſe you believe them ſtill to be real Chriſtians; as if we could not Love Mens Perſons, unleſs we fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour their Sins, and thereby perhaps through the neglect of our Duty to them, harden their Hearts therein: And ſo under the Notion of Chriſtian Charity, the true Order of a Goſpel-Church may be quite deſtroyed.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. <hi>Object.</hi> But ſome may think, I open the door of the Church too wide, and give too great incouragement for Perſons to wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from Church to Church, or to leave their preſent Communion to imbody them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into a diſtinct Church-ſtate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer</hi> 1. The ſame cauſes as will juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:50130:20"/>a ſingle Perſons removing his Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion to another Church, will alſo juſtiſie a Parties Separation to ſit down by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a Church-ſtate; otherwiſe there is no erecting of Reformed Churches to be allowed, where there was none before: Which if it be there lawful to reform, as ſurely it cannot be denied, there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Scripture nor Reaſon, as I can find, to debar a reforming party from ſettling them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the Order of a Regular Goſpel-Church, where there is one already, if they find it expedient for them.</p>
               <p>But 2. To prevent ſuch miſapprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of giving Church-members too great a Liberty. I ſhall here remind the Reader, that if he duely conſiders, what I have ſaid in this ſmall Diſcourſe, he will not find the leaſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance for Perſons to remove their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion out of Novelty, or meerly for their Pleaſures-ſake, or for Trivial Matters and Pretences; for herein the Church is bound (in faithfulneſs to Chriſt, and the Souls that are under her ſpecial care) to uſe the means directed to in the Scripture, for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving her mutual Peace and Welfare. But for real Conſcience-ſake, Separation ſhould be allowed to keep themſelves pure from corrupt and ſinful Manners, Erroneous Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines in eſſentials to Salvation, and from falſe Worſhip and irregular Ordinances; and unleſs there be a Moral Neceſſity, or a real Expediency for it, no Separation elſe is lawful; for every Member is (or ſhould
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:50130:21"/>be) in Covenant with the Church, to walk in the ways of the Lord together with them. But yet when a Church of Chriſt ſhall alter in any part of their Faith or Practice eſſential to a regular Church, the Members thereof are free from their former Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant: Not ſimply, becauſe the Church has broken the Conditions of it; (for that were to acknowledge her Members to be under an abſolute tye, while ſhe makes no Alteration of her Faith and Practice.) For as none of our Churches in Covenanting with their Members, by giving them the right hand of fellowſhip, does intend thereby ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely to bind themſelves from any future Alteration of their Faith or Practice, if in Conſcience they ſhould be otherwiſe inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; ſo the like Liberty is but equitable for the Members to have, and therefore, as there is the ſame Reaſon for it, ſo it ought to be equally taken for granted in their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanting with the Church, that each Member in Covenant hath an equal Reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Liberty of Conſcience to the Church, and neither ſide ought to impoſe on each other, for that is a making them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the perfect ſtandard of Religion, like the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">2 Pet. 5.1, 2, 3.</note> The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> exhorteth the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to take the overſight of the Flock, <hi>Not by conſtraint, but willingly; not for filthy Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre, but of a ready Mind. [Neither as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lords over Gods Heritage, but being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſamples to the Flock.]</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>That
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:50130:21"/>to ſpare you, I came not as yet unto Corinth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.23, 24. 1 Tim. 6.2, 5. 2 Tim. 2.22. Chap. 3.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Not for that we have Dominion over your Faith, but are helpers of your Joy.</hi> And <hi>Timothy</hi> was commanded as a ſingle Perſon, to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw himſelf from thoſe Profeſſors of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that were corrupt in Doctrine.</p>
               <p>Now if the Apoſtles, who were the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Pen-men of ſacred Scripture, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed Lordſhip over the Saints, and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over their Faith, Why ſhould any hold ſuch Principles, as will naturally aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume ſuch a regal Power over the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of their Brethren, as tendeth to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thral them in divers troubles; when they go about to remove their Communion from them for Conſcience-ſake, conſidering al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo they themſelves are but lately delivered from the Yoak of Perſecution? And for ſuch who make it their frequent Practice to receive Members, that remove for Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence-ſake from other Congregations (that are true Churches of Chriſt, as to their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Matter, and part of their Form,) to hold ſuch Principles as will deny their own Members Liberty of Conſcience, without their Cenſures, Snares or Inthralments to frighten their weak Brethren to continue in their Communion againſt the Light which they have received, is conſequently aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ſuch an Arbitrary Dominion over their Faith and Conſciences which neither God nor Nature hath given to them, and is not Conſonant to the Law, for doing to others as they would have others do to them in the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:50130:22"/>like Caſe. And to ſpeak the plain Truth of ſuch a Principle and Practice, it is no better then claiming a right of Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on the Conſciences of their Brethren, and a holding faſt all they have, and all they can ſo get right or wrong.</p>
               <p>And therefore ſeeing, the Light of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Reaſon with common Equity, is repugnant to ſuch an Arbitrary Dominion over the Faith and Conſciences of the Saints, and that this Principle of denying a ſingle Member his Liberty of Communion accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Light, is alſo a bar to Religious Reformation: I conceive none ſhould go about to hinder a ſingle Perſons removing from them for Conſcience-ſake any other ways, than by Arguments from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures for the Regularity of their Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; and if herein they cannot ſatisfie his Mind, I believe the Church ſhould do no more, then (if they pleaſe) to enter him in their Book departed from them, for the cauſe for which he leaveth them, for as much as his Principles are not oppoſite to any of their Eſſentials of Communion. And in Caſe they were, yet if he holdeth no Error in fundamentals to Salvation, it better ſuits with the Grace of Love and univerſal Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to one another, to let him peaceably remove his Communion, than by a harſh and ſower Spirit, to widen the Differences that are between Saints and Saints, and to fright a weak and tender Conſcience with the Cenſure of a Church; which if it be not
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:50130:22"/>according to Chriſts Inſtitutions, it is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bound in Heaven, nor ſhould it be binding on our Conſciences. But if a ſingle Member ſhould alter in his Faith or Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, from any of his Church Eſſentials of Communion, and yet ſeek to continue in the ſame Church, then to prevent the ſpreading of his Leaven to the Pollution of the Body, or their being defiled with his Errour by Participation in full Communion with him, they have ground on Non-repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to withdraw from him; and if he perſiſteth in ſuch an Errour, to purge him out from their Communion. But to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the aforeſaid Objection: What ſpiritual Comfort can any have in Church-Communion, where there is not an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Eſſentials thereof? doth not the ſweeteſt Communion depend on the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Union in Faith and Practice? why then ſhould any Chriſtians be kept in Bondage, and be deprived of the chiefeſt ends of Church-Communion, which are to glorifie God in the pureſt worſhip they can attain to the Knowledge and Practice of, and to enjoy the comfortable Communion of Saints in the Unity of Faith and of the Spirit, which is the bond of Peace?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> I ſhall preſent you with a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular inſtance of the confuſed Matter which is already Printed among us, in Mr. <hi>Keaches</hi> Book, intitled the <hi>Breach Repaired,</hi> and of ſeveral Queries made upon it in my <hi>Reply</hi> to him, with ſome Additions to them. To
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:50130:23"/>proceed therefore, I ſhall premiſe ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular things in Mr. <hi>Keaches Gold Refined,</hi> or <hi>Treatiſe of Baptiſm,</hi> Page 181, 182. where he ſaith thus, <q>Let me conclude all with one Uſe of Caution to my Brethren, that are Baptized as Believers, and yet take Liberty to walk in Communion with ſuch Churches as diſſent from them, in reſpect of this Ordinance, and ſprinkle Babes. I am more concerned about you than any other People, becauſe you ſeem to pull down with one Hand that which you build with the other — ought you not to follow the beſt and higheſt Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and cleareſt diſcovery of God, and to be in the moſt perfect and compleat Order of the Goſpel, you are able to arrive to the Knowledge of — is not Truth and Righteouſneſs to be joined with Peace and Love? Nay, and doth not my Love run out to our Brethren, in a cleaner Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel than yours.</q> And in his Treatiſe <hi>of Laying on of Hands,</hi> Page 99. he hath theſe Words. <q>Can we comfortably have Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with ſuch that oppoſe a Holy O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, or Command of God? — Ought not Communion to flow from Chriſtian Union, eſpecially in all fundamental Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Church-Conſtitution? Ought we not in theſe things to be agreed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we can in an orderly way ſit down together?</q>
               </p>
               <p>But notwithſtanding Mr. <hi>Benjamin Keach</hi> thus refuſeth Communion with thoſe that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:50130:23"/>are not under Believers-Baptiſm,<note place="margin">See my Ep. to my Reply to Mr. <hi>Keach</hi>'s Breach Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired, <hi>p. 10,</hi> &amp;c.</note> and lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of Hands, yet in his general Epiſtle to his (pretended) Anſwer to my Appen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dix, <hi>Page</hi> 9. he ſaith; <q>We do not ſay our diſſatisfied Brethren ſhall ſing with us, or we will have no fellowſhip with them: No, God forbid we ſhould impoſe on their Conſciences: We do not look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Singing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> an Eſſential of Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; it is not for the being, but for the Comfort and well being of the Church.</q> To which I there Reply to Mr. <hi>Keach, Let me ask you in your own Words,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See his darkneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed or Truth in its Primitive Purity, <hi>p. 96.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Why ſhould you have a greater eſteem for one than for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Inſtitution?</hi> If it be as you ſay, that your way of Singing is a Goſpel-Ordinance, for the Practice of the Church: Is there any Church Ordinance of Divine Worſhip, that is not eſſential to her orderly being, as well as for her Comfort and well Being? Who gave you Power to diſpence with any one Ordinance more than others? And in <hi>Page</hi> 13. of my Epiſtle, I farther tell Mr. <hi>Keach,</hi> that there are divers things that I and others cannot reconcile to the Word of God, and his confuſed Principles of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, ſome of which I offer to his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration by way of Query.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Whether it be lawful for a Chriſtian to withdraw (or remove) his Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at the Lords Table, from a Church that practiſeth any one Ordinance of Divine Worſhip, or of Church-Conſtitution, in a falſe Manner, to join with a Church that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:50130:24"/>is more pure? And whether it is his Duty, if enlightned therein, ſo to do?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whether there is any Liberty given in the Word of God, for a Chriſtian to have Communion with a Church that pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſeth any one Ordinance of Goſpel-Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, or of Church-Conſtitution, in a falſe Manner, more than of any other ſuch Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances ſo performed? and if there be, which it is, or which they are, and where the allowance is given?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whether thanking and praiſing of God, be as much an Ordinance, and of as high a Nature, as Prayer to him?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whether [the Mode of Singing] the Praiſes of God, be alſo as much an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and of as high a Nature, as Prayer?</p>
               <p n="5">5. Why it is not as unlawful to have Communion with a Church that practiſeth Singing the Praiſes of God in a falſe Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as with a Church that performeth Prayer in a falſe Manner?</p>
               <p n="6">6. Seeing you have made a Common Praiſe-Book (ſo I call it) wherein you ſay is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained ſome hundred of Sacred Hymns, out of which as I hear, is ſometimes read and ſang an Hymn in your Congregation for publick Worſhip: So if another Miniſtring Brother of your own or of another Congregation, in full Communion with you at the Lords Table, ſhould alſo make preſtinted ſet Forms of Prayer, and read them, or ſay them in the Church for publick Worſhip; I Query, Whether you would nevertheleſs hold and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:50130:24"/>continue your full Communion with ſuch a Perſon or Church as ſo uſeth ſuch humane preſtinted Forms of Prayer?</p>
               <p n="7">7. Whether it be not a worſhipping of God in a falſe Manner, and ſo unlawful, and a Sin for any of our Brethren alone by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to pray in their own or anothers ſet humane preſtinted form of Words, and if it can be proved againſt him, that he u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſuch private Prayers; Whether the Church ſhould ſtill hold their full Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with him, without Repentance for it?</p>
               <p n="8">8. Whether it be not unlawful for any of our Churches to hold full Communion with a Brother at the Lords Table, who ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times uſeth to pray with another different People, in a falſe Manner, in a ſet humane preſtinted form of Words; and if this be unlawful, whether it is not equally un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful for a Church to hold ſuch Communion with a Brother, who tho' he cannot practice Singing the Praiſes of God in as falſe a Manner in his own Church, yet he ſometimes as falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſingeth in other Congregations?</p>
               <p n="9">9. Whether [the Mode of Singing] an Hymn is a piece of Worſhip, Eſſential to the Regular and Compleat Adminiſtration of the Lords Supper? If our Singers deny this, why do ſo many of them make ſuch a ſtir about it, and commend that practice of Singing,<note place="margin">See the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to Mr. <hi>Steed</hi>'s E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. <hi>pag. 8.40, 41, 45, 47, 49.</hi>
                  </note> as they boldly ſay, from the Example of Chriſt and his Diſciples, as a perfect Pattern and Rule for us to follow? And if they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in their Conſciences, that [the Mode
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:50130:25"/>of Singing] an Hymn is ſo Eſſential to that Ordinance; How can any of thoſe Goſpel-Miniſters, as I have heard ſay, adminiſter the Lords Supper without it, and contrary to the Light of their own Conſciences di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſe with that which belongs, as they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, to Chriſts Ordinance, as if they chooſe to pleaſe Men rather than God in his Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip?</p>
               <p>I have added the more Queries, becauſe ſuch ſtating of the matter divers ways, will lay a greater Neceſſity on any who may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to anſwer them, either to diſcover the Diſcord and Confuſion of their Principles of Communion, and the natural tendency of them, or to unmaſque the farther deſigns of thoſe that are apoſtatizing from the true Worſhip of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I ſhall here humbly preſent my Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to ſome of our Baptized Churches. And</p>
               <p n="1">1. To thoſe whoſe ſixed Paſtours and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters differ from their Churches in ſome Principles, Eſſential either to the true Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of praiſing God in publick Worſhip, or to the Regular Conſtitution of a Goſpel-Church, my humble Advice to you, is. That notwithſtanding, if they rightly adminiſter all Goſpel-Ordinances, according to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of their Churches, for the preſent ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, you continue as you are: And as their Office is to watch over you in the Lord,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.17. 1 Theſ. 5.12.</note> ſo your Duty is to obey them ſo far as they rule by the Laws of Chriſt; and to continue your Affections, and abound in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:50130:25"/>Love to them and all the Saints. But yet if they put ſuch different and erroneous Principles in practice, and thereby inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the pure Communion of their Churches, contrary to their Faith and ſettled Order, or go about to diſturb your Peace with any of them; then as ye are bound to follow your Paſtours and Miniſters, only ſo far as they are followers of Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.1. Phil. 3.17.</note> ſo it is your Duty to uſe all Diligence to preſerve the Peace and right Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of your Churches againſt their Innovati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and rather than to have your Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion corrupted by them, you are to part with them and all things elſe, tho' never ſo near and dear to you.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To thoſe Churches which are deſtitute of a ſettled Paſtour: I ſhall offer this to your ſerious Conſideration, That it is a weak Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination to think that honeſt and ſincere hearted Miniſters, tho' naturally of a mild and peaceable Temper, will not labour to promote the practice of thoſe things in their Churches, which they believe to be the Will of God, for if they are faithful Men they will do it in Obedience to Chriſts Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion; wherein they are required to teach all Nations whatſoever he hath commanded them.<note place="margin">Math. 28.20.</note> And therefore if you expect that ſuch a Miniſter as you deſign to call to ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle with you, will not for the ſake of ſome in the Church who differ from him, declare and promote according to his Conſcience, the practice of all things which God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:50130:26"/>you have equal Reaſon to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that for the ſake of thoſe Perſons, he will not be faithful to his Principles; and then how can any think he will be faithful to his Church, or any thing elſe he takes in hand, any farther than it ſuits with his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate intereſt; ſo that whatever Love, Peace and Union, a Church may propoſe to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, under the care of ſuch a fixed Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtour as differs in his Principles from it, in any Eſſentials of a Regular Church. <hi>viz.</hi> Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Doctrinals to Salvation, Practicals in Divine Worſhip, or in Adminiſtrations of Goſpel-Ordinances, ſuch a Church does on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delude themſelves with an Expectation of that which they lay a Foundation to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy; for if ſuch a Paſtour be faithful to his Principles (it being irrational to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that a whole Church will be for alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their former Settlement of Communion) they will then find that his differing Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples will breed Diviſion among them, and ſo deſtroy the bond of Peace and Love, which they promiſed to themſelves from the peaceable Temper of ſuch a Paſtour: And inſtead thereof, thoſe faithful Members that are ſtill for their former Settlement, may fall into a Labyrinth of Troubles; and if they are the ſmaller part of the Church, the others will be apt to count them the diſturbers of its Peace; and perhaps when it is too late to recover the Truth and Purity of Goſpel-Worſhip and Communion that was once among them, they will mourn un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:50130:26"/>their Troubles and Temptations, and for their weakneſs in chooſing or accepting of ſuch a Paſtour, as thereby to betray the Truſt committed to them by Jeſus Chriſt, ſo far as to looſe of thoſe things he hath wrought among them, inſomuch as reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their publick Truſt of the Goſpel,<note place="margin">2 John 8.</note> as Members of a viſible Church of Chriſt, they will come ſo ſhort of holding faſt that which they have received,<note place="margin">Rev. 3.11.</note> that no Man take their Crown, as that they cannot give ſo good an account of their Stewardſhip, as that evil Servant did,<note place="margin">Math. 25, 25, 26.</note> who rendred again what he had received of his Lord.</p>
               <p>Therefore knowing the aptneſs of many People to follow others Examples, from their Affections to them, more than from the real Judgment and Underſtanding they have of their Principles; and conſidering the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience ſome have had of the reſtleſs en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of their Miniſters, to leaven their Churches with thoſe Principles wherein they differ from them; and the Obligation of Conſcience they are under, according to their Light, to declare the whole Counſel of God to the People under their care;<note place="margin">Acts 20.26, 27.</note> I conclude it highly concerns thoſe Churches that have yet their choice to make for the Miniſtration of Goſpel-Ordinances, to ſeek for ſuch Perſons as are one with them in the Unity of the Faith, and of the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Goſpel-Inſtitutions. For whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Affections you may have to any Perſon, yet above all things you ought to be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:50130:27"/>to the Truth, as ye have received it in your Conſciences, and not by any means to be led aſide to betray the Purity of the Goſpel committed to your Truſt, ſo far as to put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it into the Power of any Perſon to be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually working (perhaps while you and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are lull'd aſleep in the pretended Bed of Charity) the overthrow and confuſion of any eſſential part of the Religion you profeſs. Beſides, a Paſtour ſhould be qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified, according to the Word of God, which ſaith, <hi>A Biſhop muſt be blameleſs, as the Steward of God — holding faſt the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Word, as he hath been taught, that he may be able by ſound Doctrine, both to exhort and to convince the gain-ſayers.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tit. 1.7, 9, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>For there are many unruly, and vain-talkers, and Deceivers, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially they of the Circumciſion: Whoſe Mouths muſt be ſtopped.</hi> Now conſider, that one great qualification of an Elder, is to be able to ſtop the Mouths of Gain-ſayers. And therefore none who differ from their Church in any eſſential Principles of her Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are fit for the Office of an Elder in it, for ſuch a one in the Matters of difference, is principled rather to gain-ſay the Church, than other Perſons that oppoſe the Faith or Practice of it.</p>
               <p>Moreover the Zeal of others, which are for the common way of Singing, ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke us to promote the pure Intereſt of Chriſt among our Churches, for they have uſed di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence to improve the Beneſit of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Fund, for Learning of ſuch young Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:50130:27"/>the Knowledge of the Tongues, the better to ſit them for the Goſpel Miniſtry; who have ſucked in that apoſtatizing Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Singing, and I have been told that ſome of them have gone to School to learn it by Art in and about <hi>Briſtol,</hi> or the We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern parts of this Land, and if I am not miſinformed, there were eight in number for common ſet form ſinging, two of which were advanced by more private means, then the publick Fund; and Mr. <hi>Keach</hi> has pleaded ſo much for Art in Divine Worſhip,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>See his Book inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled,</hi> the Breach Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired in Gods Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, <hi>Page</hi> 183, 184.</note> that if the Spirit of the Lord does not lift up a ſpiritual ſtandard againſt it, we may fear the increaſe of Artificial Worſhip in our Churches; for he ſaith, <q>There is I muſt 'tell you, an Art in ſpeaking; and no Man but has need to learn, and be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to ſpeak as he ought — eſpecially when he ſpeaks about Divine Things. — Alſo there is an Art in preaching; and all young Men when they begin to take upon them that work, need Inſtruction how to handle a Doctrine. And (ſaith he) ſo I may ſay in Praying too.</q> So that we ſee, how naturally the Art of ſinging, which he is there pleading for, does draw Men in to plead for an Art in Praying too. And as I have ſaid in my Reply to him,<note place="margin">See my Book, <hi>Page 18.</hi>
                  </note> is not this a forward ſtep (for him or others that may (if the Lord of his Mercy does not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent) hereafter build upon this Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,) to bring into uſe a preſtinted Form of Prayer for Goſpel-Worſhip; for if Nature
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:50130:28"/>and Grace may and ought to be improved by Art, to expreſs the Matter of our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to God; what Art can he mean, or can any others think is beſt for Prayer, than to uſe an Artificial Form of Words? I menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe things to ſhew the danger that we are in of looſing the true ſpiritual Worſhip of God, by the apoſtatizing of ſome in our Profeſſion to the Errour of preſtinted Forms of Singing. And if we do not incourage ſuch gracious Brethren, as may be found among us better principled (whether with or without the Knowldge of other Tongues) to improve their Gifts, which through the Bleſſing of God may be fit for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Service of our Churches, many of them are like to crumble away for want of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſuitable to their Principles; and thoſe others, which have been advanced to the Miniſtry by the publick Fund, will have the greater opportunity through the neceſſities of our Churches to infect our Profeſſion with their Error of common ſet form Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (and I fear with mixed Communion too, which ſeem like twins to go hand in hand together.) As for their [Mode] of of Singing, I have largely ſhewed, that which was never anſwered by any of them, and plainly proved in my Reply to Mr. <hi>Benjamin Keaches</hi> Book of Singing, Intitled the <hi>Breach Repaired,</hi> &amp;c. That we have no Command nor Example, neither under the Law, nor under the Goſpel for the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and all the People to ſing with u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:50130:28"/>Voices together in the ſettled worſhip of God in his Church. And that his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon way of Singing, is not that Mode of ſpiritual ſinging which was uſed in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles time, nor is it the natural, but an Artificial Mode of Worſhip: And alſo that we have not the leaſt ground to conclude, that Chriſt and his Diſciples at or after the Lords Supper did ſing the Hymn or Praiſe, which they gave to God, for thoſe Texts, <hi>Math.</hi> 26.30. <hi>Mark</hi> 14.26. and <hi>Acts</hi> 16.25. are not rightly tranſlated in our laſt Bibles, which are witneſſed againſt by many of our old Engliſh Bibles, and many learned Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours, as I have abundantly ſhewed in my a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Reply to Mr. <hi>Keach.</hi> But to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn. It is therefore high time for all that have any Love for the Truth and Purity of Goſpel-worſhip, to awake out of ſleep; for the neceſſities of many Churches call upon us earneſtly to ſeek the Lord by Humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Faſtings and Prayers; that he would graciouſly raiſe up Miniſters, not only ſound in the Faith, but in all their Principles of Divine Worſhip, in the Spirit of Love and Meekneſs. And tho' we may find ſome of our Miniſters, and other Brethren, that are for the new Modelling of our Churches with their formal Worſhip, and mixed Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion to decline this Work with us, by Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon their different Principles cannot join with our particular Requeſts relating there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto; yet this ſhould in no wiſe hinder our People from flocking together, and crying
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:50130:29"/>fervently to the Lord for the pourings forth of the Holy Spirit (according to his promiſe) to bear a lively Teſtimony againſt all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs and falſe worſhip,<note place="margin">Iſa. 44.3, to 6. Ch. 59.21. Eph. 4.11, 12, 13. Iſa. 59.19, 20, 21. Jer. 3.15.</note> and to give us Paſtours according to his heart, which ſhall feed his People with Knowledg and Underſtanding, even ſuch as ſhall worſhip him in Spirit and Truth, without any mixture of humane Forms and meer Inventions of men. For if inſtead of ſound Elders we ſhould have only thoſe for the publick ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God that are for a piece of falſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and mixed communion, what elſe can be expected from new Converts and thoſe who joyn themſelves to our Churches, but that through Love and Affections to their Miniſters they will ſuck in their Erroneous Principles, as ſad Experience hath ſhewed, and ſo in time will overturn the former or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and ſettlement of our Churches, and put back that bleſſed Reformation which God has wrought among us, and which many pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Saints have ſuffered for, that the Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Goſpel (which ſome are now betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) might be handed down to future ages.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> I ſhall leave a few things to the ſerious conſideration of thoſe who have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the manifeſtation of the ſpecial Grace of God in Chriſt to their ſouls, through faith which worketh by love, and yet are walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at large in neglect of his holy Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as if they were left to Chriſtians liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to obey or reject them at their pleaſures. Let me ask a few Queſtions for thee to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:50130:29"/>in thine own Conſcience,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.15, 16.</note> which ſhall either accuſe or elſe excuſe thee in the day when God ſhall judge the ſecrets of men by Jeſus Chriſt, according to the Goſpel. Why art thou partial in Gods laws or in Chriſts inſtitutions,<note place="margin">Mal. 2.9.</note> ſo as to pick and chooſe which of them thou wilt obey? Remember,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.6.</note> 
                  <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Then ſhall I not be aſhamed, when I have reſpect unto all thy Commandments.</hi> Wilt thou partake of the Benefit of the publick Prayers of the Saints, and of the Miniſtration of the Goſpel of Chriſt in his Church, and not put to thy helping hand to ſupport it in the World, and to convey it down to future ages? what had become of thy precious ſoul, and many thouſands more, if our late Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers had bin of thy Mind? how ſhould the true worſhip of God have bin maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and how little preaching ſhould we have in our preſent day, if Chriſtians did not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>body themſelves into Societies to encourage the Goſpel Miniſters? for where can their light beſt appear if not on a Goſpel Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick? No marvel, Soul, if thou haſt not peace of Conſcience and ſtrength of Grace againſt the power of Sins and Temptations, if thy feet are not found in the ways of Chriſt, whoſe ways are ways of pleaſantneſs,<note place="margin">Prov. 3.17. Ch. 10.29. Iſa. 64.5.</note> and all his paths are peace and ſtrength to the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right. There God has ſaid he meets his people that remember him in his ways, and Chriſt has much intailed his gracious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence on the faithful obedience of his Saints. <hi>He that hath my Commandments,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 14.21.</note> 
                  <hi>and keepeth
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:50130:30"/>them, he it is that loveth we: And he that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth me ſhall be loved of my Father, and I will love him, and will manifeſt my ſelf to him. — If a man love me, he will keep my words: And my Father will love him; and we will come unto him, and make our abode with him.</hi> And therefore the more obedient a Soul is, the more of Chriſts fulneſs he ſhall receive,<note place="margin">John 1.16.</note> and Grace for Grace.</p>
               <p>But 2. If thou ſtandeſt off from Church-Communion, becauſe thou thinkeſt thy ſelf unworthy of it, or unmeet for it, or till thou haſt a ſpecial inſpiration to thruſt thee forth in thy duty; my Anſwer is, that in this ſnare I was intangled my ſelf for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers years, but at laſt I was ſatisfied in my Conſcience; that ſeeing I had true ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Faith and Light in Goſpel Ordinances, my perſonal unworthineſs through the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity of Nature was no ſufficient Ground for me to neglect the Inſtitutions of Chriſt, and that I could not rationally expect any extraordinary motions to do that which the Word of God did plainly expreſs to be my Duty. Beſides, for Chriſtians to wait for a more than ordinary impulſe of Spirit, to thruſt them forth in their Duty, when clearly expreſt in the Holy Scriptures, is thro' weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Faith, a Tempting God to confirm his written Will by extraordinary Inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is a Sin, <hi>Math.</hi> 4.7.</p>
               <p>Moreover, I ſhall farther remove this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.27. <hi>Whoſoever ſhall eat this Bread, and drink this Cup of the Lord un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:50130:30"/>ſhall be guilty of the Body and Blood of the Lord.</hi> This unworthineſs cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect our natural infirmities, for then the beſt of men would be excluded from that Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; but the unworthineſs there mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned is deſcribed to us in the ſame Chapter to be, Diviſions and Drunkeneſs,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>See</hi> ver. 18.20, 21, 22, 33.</note> and ſuch like Diſorders as ſhould not be ſuffered in a Goſpel-Church, or that ſhew they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe the Church of God. And therefore Chriſtians having light in Goſpel Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, tho' they are but weak in Faith and Babes in Chriſt, and have not yet attained to the Faith of Aſſurance of their Election,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.10.</note> or to the clear witneſſings of the Spirit of God with their Spirits,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.16.</note> that they are the Children of God, yet having the true Faith of cleaving to Chriſt with full purpoſe of heart, and of reliance on his death and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits for Salvation and eternal life, thoſe have a right to full Communion with the Church, at the Lords Table and we are bound to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them,<note place="margin">Rom. 14.1.</note> but not to doubtful Diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: But.</p>
               <p>If thou art one within the viſible pale of the Church, and ſuch a wonderful and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible thing is therein, or ſhall happen, as was in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> tho' in a different manner, the Prophets propheſied falſly,<note place="margin">Jere. 5.31.</note> and the Prieſts bear Rule by their means, and the people loved to have it ſo. As the Lord ſaid to them, ſo will I ſay to thee, if then thou art of their Spirit, what wilt thou do in the end thereof, when the Lord ſhall viſit for
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:50130:31"/>theſe things? canſt thou bear, yea like and plead for an Alteration in thy Church-Conſtitution, or in Gods worſhip, becauſe thy Paſtour will have it ſo. Take heed leſt thou giveſt ground to ſay of thee as it was ſaid to <hi>Iſrael:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 3.12. Ch. 9.16.</note> 
                  <hi>O my People, they which lead thee, cauſe thee to err, and deſtroy the way of thy paths. — and they that are led of them are deſtroyed.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.22.</note> Brethren, beware leſt ye provoke, the Lord to Jealouſy! are ye ſtronger than he?<note place="margin">Deut. 12.32.</note> hath he not ſaid, what things ſoever I command you, obſerve to do it? Thou ſhalt not add thereto, nor diminiſh from it. And have we not divers inſtances of his ſore Diſpleaſure for breaking his Rule of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as in <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lev. 7.11, to 19.</note> who for offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of ſtrange fire, died before the Lord? And might not ſome have thought it a ſmall matter to have eaten of the Peace or Thank-offering after the firſt day, or of the Vow-offering, if any of it had been left on the third day, but we ſee how great an offence it was to make ſo ſmall an Addition to Gods Ordinance, as that it ſhould not be accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, neither ſhould it be imputed to him that offered it: It ſhould be an Abomination, and that ſoul ſhould bear his iniquity. Moreover, we read how the Lord ſmote above fifty thouſand of the men of <hi>Beth-ſhe-meſh</hi> for but looking into his Ark, and how <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah</hi> loſt his life for touching the Ark of God,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 6.6. 1 Sam. 6.19. 2 Chr. 26.16.</note> becauſe they ſought him not after the due manner: And how <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah</hi> the King for medling with Gods Ordinance, and burning
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:50130:31"/>incenſe before the Lord,<note place="margin">1 Chr. 15.13.</note> contrary to his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed Will, was ſmote with leproſy unto his dying Day. And Chriſt tells us,<note place="margin">Mat. 159.</note> that in vain they do worſhip him teaching for Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines the Commandments of Men. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>to the Law and to the Teſtimony:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 8.20.</note> 
                  <hi>If they ſpeak not according to this Word, it is becauſe there is no light in them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 4.24.</note> and let us keep the Commandments of God and worſhip him in Spirit and in Truth,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4 8.</note> for Godlineſs is profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble unto all things, having promiſe of the Life that now is, and of that which is to come.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
               <p>AFter I had penned the preceeding Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, meeting with ſome other Motives, I thought it neceſſary to add a brief Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe on two particular Caſes: The <hi>Firſt</hi> to ſhew, that it is the Duty of Goſpel-Miniſters and all true Believers, in Order to Church-Communion, to ſubject themſelves to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of Water-Baptiſm. The <hi>Second</hi> is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Exceſs in Apparel. And <hi>Firſt,</hi> I ſhall premiſe ſome few things that are worth our Obſervation which I find in Mr. <hi>William Kif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fins</hi> Book, Intitled <hi>A Sober Diſcourſe of Right to Church-Communion:</hi> Where in his <hi>Epiſtle</hi> he ſaith, <q>The ſence I have of my own weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and inability, would have been a Bar to me to appear in this publick way, did I not
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:50130:32"/>ſee a neceſſity lying upon me for the Truths ſake, and the ſakes of many, by reaſon of ſome that have lately riſen up to weaken, if not make void that great Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Baptiſm, by endeavouring to maintain, that all Perſons that believe, altho' they never did, nor do practice the ſame, may partake of the Ordinance of the Lords Supper, and all other Goſpel inſtituted Duties: A Notion, not only contrary to the primitive Pattern, but the conſtant Practice of all that ever proſeſſed the Chriſtian Religion, or that own the Scriptures to be the Rule of Faith and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice.</q> And ſpeaking ſomewhat of the like nature in <hi>p.</hi> 3. he alſo ſaith, <q>We ſhall therefore direct this Diſcourſe to our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Brethren, of the baptized way on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</q> And in <hi>page</hi> 13, 14. he argueth, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <q>If unbaptized Perſons may be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to all Church Priviledges, does not ſuch a Practice plainly ſuppoſe that it is unneceſſary? — The Baptiſts (if once ſuch a Belief prevails) would be eaſily tempted to lay aſide that reproachful Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice. — And challenge their Church Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion by Vertue of their Faith only; and ſuch as baptize Infants would be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to diſcontinue the Practice, when once they are perſwaded, that their Children may be regular Church-members without it; — and by conſequence be in a likely condition to looſe one of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, which would eaſily make way
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:50130:32"/>for the loſs of the other, both having an equal ſanction in Scripture; and the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments that diſanul the one, will deſtroy the other, and conſequently all Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Modes of Worſhip, and laſtly, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion it ſelf.</q> And in <hi>page</hi> 118. In anſwer to an Objection, he ſaith, <q>This Objection ſuppoſes things very dangerous. As, that holineſs without Baptiſm inveſts a right to other Ghurch-Ordinances, which is not to be ſuppoſed, for Chriſt the Lamb of God was holy in the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and in him was found no ſin, yet he was baptized before he entred upon his publick Miniſtry, which is a moſt illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Example, and the Pattern which the Saints followed; for in a word, the great Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> and all thoſe primitive Saints recorded by the Spirit to be Believers, and therefore holy; were nevertheleſs Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, which might have been forborn, but that it was an indiſpenſable Duty.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>Secondly,</hi> It ſeemeth ſtrange to me, that any profeſſing Obedience to Goſpel-Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances ſhould ſo far countenance others in the neglect of a poſitive Inſtitution of Chriſt, as to plead for Church-Communion with Chriſtians, without Baptiſm, when our Lord hath plainly commanded his Apoſtles and Miniſters to the end of the World ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Go ye therefore and teach all Nations,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 28.19, 20.</note> 
                  <hi>Baptizing them, — teaching them to obſerve all things whatſoever I have commanded you: And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, I am with you alway even unto the end of the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:50130:33"/>World.</hi> For ſeeing the Diſciples of Chriſt were commanded to Baptize as well as to Preach, and to teach others ſucceſſively to do the ſame; It is undeniably clear, if Scripture and Reaſon may take Place, that the Goſpel Miniſters ought to Baptize thoſe that obey their Doctrine;<note place="margin">Acts a. 38, 41.</note> as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid, <hi>Repent, and be baptized every one of you — then they that gladly received his Word, were Baptized; and the ſame day there were added unto them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout three thouſand Souls. And they continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſtedfaſtly in the Apoſtles Doctrine and Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and in breaking of Bread, and in Prayer.</hi> Here we find thoſe new Converts were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded every of one them to be Baptized, and this way they were added to the Primitive Church of Chriſt at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> which was the Pattern for all Goſpel-Churches to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in after Ages. For there were the twelve Apoſtles, who were endowed with the extraordinary Gifts of the Holy Spirit, to ſhew us the perfect pattern of Gods Houſe: And this was the Church that ſaid, <hi>It ſeemeth good to the Holy Ghoſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 15.22, 28.</note> 
                  <hi>and to us, to lay upon you no greater Burthen then theſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary things;</hi> and from this Pattern (given as it were in the Mount of God) we find Baptiſm was commanded as the entring Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance into Church Communion, or upon Confeſſion of Faith before it; for baptized Believers (tho' the true viſible matter of a Goſpel-Church) were not always imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately formed into a Goſpel-Church Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, for this was ſometimes a work of time,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:50130:33"/>as we have an Inſtance, how <hi>Paul</hi> baptized the twelve Diſciples at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and went into the Synagogue,<note place="margin">Acts 19.1, to 10.</note> and ſpake boldly for the ſpace of three Months, before he ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated the Diſciples from the Multitude.</p>
               <p>Moreover, we have ſeveral other Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts and Examples, that do confirm the Ordinance of Baptiſm, immediately to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Converſion and Faith in Chriſt:<note place="margin">Acts 8.35, to 39.</note> As when <hi>Philip</hi> Preached unto the Eunuch, and he believed, he was immediately Baptized. And when <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his Friends were Converted,<note place="margin">Act. 10.44, 48. Act. 16.14, 15, 32, 33. Ch. 18.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Peter</hi> commanded them to be Baptized: And ſo we find <hi>Lydia</hi> and her Houſhold, and the Jaylor and his Houſhold were Baptized, immediately after their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion. And all theſe inſtances plainly ſhew, that Water-Baptiſm was adminiſtred to Converted Believers, before they were in Church-Order to receive the Ordinance of the Lords Supper; and 'tis called a put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on Chriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> by a viſible Profeſſion; and ſignifieth our dying unto Sin,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.27. Col. 2.12. Rom. 6.3, to 7. Joh. 3 3.5. Mark 16.15, 16.</note> and living in newneſs of Life unto God: As alſo our being born of the Spirit; and all theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>note Baptiſm to be the firſt viſible Sign of a Believer in Chriſt, and it is appointed to accompany the Preaching of the Goſpel, as a Chriſtian Badge on all that ſhall believe. And it was called a Foundation-Principle, <hi>viz.</hi> of a viſible Church-ſtate,<note place="margin">Act. 2.38, 41. Ch. 8.12. Ch. 18.8.</note> the matter whereof was, and ſtill ſhould be baptized Believers. And there being not the leaſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in the New Teſtament, of any one
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:50130:34"/>Perſon that was ever added to a Goſpel-Church without Water-Baptiſm, nor that any Goſpel-Church was ever gathered, but of baptized Believers; to exclude it as no entring Ordinance into Church-Communion, againſt ſo many clear Commands and Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples on Sacred Record; which ſhews it is immediately to follow believing in Chriſt, will lay a Foundation to deny all Goſpel-Ordinances, and the Holy Scriptures them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be of uſe to us, to diſcover the Truth of Goſpel-Worſhip and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
               <p n="1">I. <hi>Object.</hi> Is from <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.1. <hi>Him that is weak in the Faith receive you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer,</hi> To this Scripture Mr. <hi>Will. Kif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin</hi> in his aforeſaid <hi>Sober Diſcourſe,</hi> ſaith, <q>The weakneſs ſpoken of in the Text, hath Relation only to thoſe Miſtakes that did attend ſome of them, touching a Liberty of eating, or not eating of Meats, or the keeping or not keeping of Days, which were things in themſelves of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different Nature, the doing or not doing of which was not Sin, as the Apoſtle in that Chapter plainly ſhews; and hath no Relation to the Order of Worſhip preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by Chriſt, much leſs to the Practice, or not Practice of Ordinances, for then the meaning of the Apoſtle ſhould be, if they did Practice, or not Practice, it was all one, there was no Sin in the Matter. — But to bring this Text, to prove a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of receiving any that are Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:50130:34"/>altho' never ſo ignorant of the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and inſtituted Worſhip of Chriſt, and the Order preſcribed by him, is to wring Blood out of it, and not that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Truth that is manifeſted by it.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>Object.</hi> Is from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13. <hi>For by one Spirit are we all Baptized into one Body, whether we be Jews or Gentiles, whether we be Bond or Free, and have been all made to drink into one Spirit.</hi> Here is (ſay ſome) a Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm mentioned, by which they are brought, or initiated into this Body, <hi>viz.</hi> the Church;<note place="margin">Ver. 28.</note> but ſay they, it is the Baptiſm of the Spirit, and not of Water.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer,</hi> That which is called the Baptiſm of the Holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">Acts 1.5. Ch. 2.12</note> were thoſe extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Gifts of the Holy Spirit which Chriſt had promiſed his Diſciples they ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive not many days hence, and was fulſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led on the day of Pentecoſt,<note place="margin">Acts 10.44, 45, 46</note> and given to others afterwards. And we no where find the common Gifts and Graces of the Holy Spirit, called Baptiſm: And therefore this Baptiſm in the Text (having ſome Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to theſe excellent Gifts, as appears in the preceeding Verſes) it muſt be underſtood either only of thoſe extraordinary Gifts of the Spirit in the Miniſtry, whereby the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Goſpel Miniſters were qualified, to break down the middle Wall of Partition, and unite all, both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> Bond and Free, that were Effectually called, into one Body or viſible Church-ſtate; or rather thus, that the Apoſtle ſpeaks of the <hi>Gentiles</hi>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:50130:35"/>with himſelf, and other <hi>Jews,</hi> that through the extraordinary Miniſtration of the Spirit were baptized with Water-Baptiſm into one Body. For ſeeing it cannot rationally be ſuppoſed, that thoſe of the Church of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth</hi> to whom the Apoſtle could not ſpeak <hi>as unto Spiritual,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.1, 2.</note> 
                  <hi>but as unto Carnal, even as unto Babes in Chriſt:</hi> Or that every individu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Believer included in the Text, was Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized <hi>[with]</hi> the Spirit, but as its ſaid <hi>[by]</hi> the Spirit, as the efficient cauſe. It then follows, that the Baptiſm in the Text, muſt be taken for Water-Baptiſm; conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering alſo,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.1.</note> that thoſe Brethren the Apoſtle wrote unto with himſelf and other <hi>Jews,</hi> are ſaid in the Text in Diſtinction to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, to <hi>have been all made to drink into one Spirit;</hi> which Expreſſion is far ſhort of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all perſonally baptized with the Baptiſm of the Spirit; and therefore to me it clearly appears, that the Baptiſm ſpoken of in the Objection, muſt be taken for Water Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm as its ſaid,<note place="margin">Act. 18.8.</note> that when the <hi>Corinthians</hi> had the Goſpel preached to them, many of them hearing believed and were Baptized, <hi>viz.</hi> not many of the Church then already formed into an orderly Church-ſtate,<note place="margin">Ver. 10. 1 Cor. 3 6, 10. Ch. 1.12.</note> but many of the People of that City Believed and were Baptized, and ſo the Apoſtle laid the Foundation of the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> and planted the ſame, which <hi>Apollo</hi> water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p n="3">III. <hi>Object.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, That Chriſt ſent him not to Baptize, but to preach the Goſpel, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.17.</p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:50130:35"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer,</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> was Baptized himſelf,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.4, 5.</note> and he tells us, that there is one Body, one Spirit, one Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſm, <hi>viz.</hi> one Water-Baptiſm, becauſe it is here diſtinguiſhed from the Spirit, as pertaining to the Body, or dwelling in its Gifts and Graces in the Church. And he alſo inſtructed the twelve Diſciples at <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> to be Baptized,<note place="margin">Acts 19.3, 4.</note> tho' they were Baptized before with <hi>Johns</hi> Baptiſm. And he Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed <hi>Criſpus</hi> and <hi>Gaius,</hi> and the Houſhold of <hi>Stephanus,</hi> ſo that if he were not ſent to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.14, 16.</note> he acted beyond his particular Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, and had not ſo much Authority as other Goſpel Miniſters received from the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Commiſſion given to them; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtles meaning is, That tho' his Commiſſion to Preach and Baptize was as large as others, yet his work was not ſo much actually to Baptize and ſpend his time in that Service, as to preach the Goſpel, he being extraordinarily Gifted thereunto; for he was counted the chief Speaker,<note place="margin">Acts 14.12.</note> and thoſe Miniſters that were his Companions being qualified to Baptize, were doubtleſs helpful to him in that Service; for when he preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> it is ſaid (not only <hi>Criſpus,</hi> and all his Houſe believed, but) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the <hi>Corinthians</hi> believed and were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized. So that <hi>Pauls</hi> Expreſſion, that he was not ſent to Baptize, is to be expounded as its ſaid of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Joh. 4.1, 2.</note> that tho' he made and haptized more Diſciples than <hi>John,</hi> yet Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus himſelf baptized not, but his Diſciples,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:50130:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>and as when <hi>Peter</hi> had preached there were other Goſpel Miniſters with him, who did Baptize, otherwiſe <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf could not have baptized in one day about three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Souls. And ſo we find,<note place="margin">Acts 2.41.</note> that <hi>Paul</hi> had <hi>Silas</hi> and <hi>Timotheus</hi> with him at <hi>Corinth,</hi> when ſo many of them were Baptized, and that as a Son with the Father, ſo had <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy</hi> ſerved with him in the Goſpel. And therefore the Text being fairly and moſt properly thus expounded, the aforeſaid Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection is invalid, and cannot prove an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to Church Communion, without the Ordinance of Water-Baptiſm.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. <hi>Object.</hi> Gal. 3.27. <hi>As many of you as have been Baptized into Chriſt, have put on Chriſt:</hi> From whence it hath been ſaid that ſome of the Members of thoſe Churches, were not Baptized.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer,</hi> To explain the Mind of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, I ſhall here recite the preceeding Words, <hi>Ver.</hi> 26. <hi>For ye are all the Children of God by Faith in Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> and then it follows, <hi>Ver.</hi> 27. <hi>For as many of you as have been Baptized into Chriſt, have put on Chriſt.</hi> From whence I obſerve, that the Word [all] <hi>ver.</hi> 26. is in <hi>ver.</hi> 28. put for the ſame Perſons to ſhew there is no Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of Acceptance of Perſons, in Chriſt Jeſus, whether <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Greeks,</hi> Bond or Free, Male or Female, all are one, and by Faith in Chriſt are alike, the adopted Children of God, and ſo the Word [all] muſt be underſtood in <hi>ver.</hi> 26. as hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:50130:36"/>Relation to <hi>ver.</hi> 28. and not of every individual Member of thoſe Churches of <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latia,</hi> for who can think they were all, <hi>viz.</hi> every individual Perſon of them really the Children of God, ſeeing they were ſo far Apoſtatized, as that the Apoſtle ſaid he was afraid of them, leaſt he had beſtowed on them labour in vain. And then,<note place="margin">Ch. 4.11.</note> if the Word [all] muſt be reſtrained to all thoſe only, or to ſo many as were the Children of God by true Faith in Chriſt, it is put for no more than the Word [many] <hi>viz.</hi> for ſo many or all of them, as had received both the inward Grace, as well as the outward putting on the viſible Profeſſion of it by Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Baptiſm. And the like inſtance we have that the Word [all] is reſtrained [to many] <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.18. compared with <hi>ver.</hi> 19. And therefore the aforeſaid Scripture can be no Proof that any Perſons were admitted into Church-Communion without Water-Baptiſm.</p>
               <p>And farther to clear this Objection, from <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3. There is this to ſay, that that Epiſtle was written to all that were in <hi>Rome,</hi> beloved of God, called to be Saints, which comprehendeth a Direction of that Epiſtle,<note place="margin">Rom. 16.5, 14, 15.</note> not only to one or more particular Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es in the Order of the Goſpel, but to all the Saints in <hi>Rome,</hi> beloved and called of God, whether within, or for want of time and growth of Grace and Knowledge, were then waiting on the Miniſtry of the Goſpel for farther Light, without the Pale of the Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:50130:37"/>Church; and therefore the Apoſtle might properly ſay, that ſo many of us, <hi>viz.</hi> of all thoſe Saints in general, as were ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered into a Church-ſtate, and baptized into Jeſus Chriſt were baptized into his Death,<note place="margin">Ver. 4, 5.</note> 
                  <hi>viz.</hi> into the likeneſs of his Death by Water-baptiſm; and thus the Word [many] may be taken in its moſt proper Sence, without the leaſt implication that unbaptized Chriſtians were admitted to full Communion with the Church at the Lords Table.</p>
               <p n="5">V. <hi>Object.</hi> The Church in the Wilderneſs received Members the way which was not preſcribed, but directly againſt the revealed Mind of God, yet ſtood a true Church and their Members true Members. For this Church had Circumciſion for their entring Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,<note place="margin">Gen. 17.13, 14. Exo. 12.</note> and the uncircumciſed were utterly forbidden to eat the Paſſover, yet this Church received Members without and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than by this entring Ordinance, they alſo admitted them to the Paſſover ſo long as forty Years without it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer,</hi> It is expreſly ſaid, That <hi>all the People</hi> (viz. <hi>the Males</hi>) <hi>that came out (of Egypt) were Circumciſed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joſh. 5.4, to 8. Exod. 14.10, 11, 12.</note> 
                  <hi>but all the People that were born in the Wilderneſs by the way, as they came forth out of Egypt, them they had not circumciſed. — becauſe they had not circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed them by the way.</hi> From whence I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that ſeeing the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were not Circumciſed by the way, and yet that all were Circumciſed that came out of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:50130:37"/>
                  <hi>Egypt,</hi> it muſt needs follow, that they were Circumciſed in <hi>Egypt,</hi> as the Lord comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 12.48, to 52. which tho' it is there rehearſed, after the account of the Deſtruction of the firſt-born of <hi>Egypt, &amp;c.</hi> yet Circumciſion was commanded be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as appeareth by the two laſt verſes of that <hi>Chapter.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 17.9, 10.</note> And ſo it was from its firſt Inſtitution to <hi>Abraham,</hi> again renewed by <hi>Moſes,</hi> as an entring Ordinance into a Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church-ſtate, and the Priviledges there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; but the occaſion of the diſuſe of this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance afterwards in the Wilderneſs, not being expreſſed as I can find in any part of the Scriptures, we muſt conclude, that as God never approved of the Wilful neglect of the leaſt of his Commandments, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he again commanded <hi>Iſrael</hi> to be Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, when they were entring in to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs the promiſed Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> we have not the leaſt incouragement from <hi>Iſraels</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Diſobedience in the Wilderneſs (which is ſo much in general,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10. Heb. 3.8, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> as well as in ſome particulars complained of in the Holy Scriptures) nor from Gods renewing his Command to <hi>Iſrael</hi> for Circumciſion, to Countenance the neglect of any Goſpel Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, but contrariwiſe in Caſe of any Declenſion among Believers, to ſtir up one another to a Reformation, according to the Inſtitutions of Chriſt, and the Primitive Pattern of Gods ſpiritual Houſe on Sacred Record.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. <hi>Object.</hi> It is farther ſaid, that <hi>Aaron</hi>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:50130:38"/>let the offering for Sin be burnt,<note place="margin">Lev. 10. Ch. 6.26.</note> that ſhould have indeed been eaten; yet becauſe he could not do it to his Edification, <hi>Moſes</hi> was Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer, Moſes</hi> was content not ſimply, becauſe <hi>Aaron</hi> had done contrary to the Commandment, but becauſe <hi>Aaron</hi> had ſuch things befallen him that day, as that it would not have been accepted of God for him to eat the Offering, as we find by <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons</hi> Anſwer to <hi>Moſes, Lev.</hi> 10.19. And this being on the extraordinary occaſion of <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons</hi> looſing his two Sons,<note place="margin">Lev. 10.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi> who died before the Lord for Offering of ſtrange Fire; it is moſt likely, either this Sin of his Houſe, or thereby was occaſioned ſome unholineſs, or ſome other uncleanneſs happened to <hi>Aaron</hi> (tho' it is not particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly expreſſed) as did by Law prevent him from eating of the Holy Sacrifice, <hi>Lev.</hi> 6.18, 27. And ſo it is under the Adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Goſpel, that in caſe of Sin, or any Uncleanneſs, prohibited the Communion of the Church by the Laws of Chriſt, the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender (until there be Repentance to take it off) ought not to partake of the Holy Supper, tho' it be commanded as a Goſpel-Ordinance; yea, a whole Church may ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpend it for a ſeaſon, rather then to partake of it with ſuch evils as are prohibited their Communion by the Laws of Chriſt; and who will ſay, that ſuch a Suſpenſion of the Ordinance will be charged as her Sin, if ſhe be neceſſitated thereunto, for want of a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:50130:38"/>or Miniſtring Brother gifted and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified for that Service. And therefore from what hath been here ſaid, we may conclude, that the aforeſaid Old Teſtament Caſes have no. Example in them, as ſhadows to juſtifie any Believers admittance into Church-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion without Water-Baptiſm; but that thoſe and all other Scriptures muſt be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, ſo as to preſerve the Concord of Sacred Writ with the plain and poſitive In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and their Examples with the Primitive Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, who clearly witneſs to the Ordinance of Water-Baptiſm preceeding Church-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>Againſt Exceſs in Apparel.</head>
            <p>THat Ornaments of Apparel in a Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Sence may be allowed, ſo far as they ſuit and rather tend to the Credit and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of the Goſpel, and that a difference in Apparel is not unlawful, according to the State and Circumſtances of the Saints, is not denyed. But yet whatever Ornaments are inconſiſtent with Modeſty, Gravity and Sobriety, and are a ſcandal to Religion, ought to be caſt off, as being a defilement to Believers, and an Abominaton in the ſight of God,<note place="margin">Iſa. 3.16. Zeph. 1.8.</note> who reproved and brought his Scourge upon the Daughters of <hi>Zion,</hi> for
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:50130:39"/>the Bravery, Haughtineſs and Pride of their Attire, and by the Prophet hath ſaid, he would puniſh all ſuch as were cloathed with ſtrange Apparel. And the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>I will therefore that — Women adorn themſelves in modeſt Apparel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>with Shame-facedneſs and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety; not with Broidered Hair, or Gold, or Pearls, or coſtly Array; but (which becometh Women profeſſing Godlineſs) with good works. — And whoſe adorning,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.3, 4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>let it not be the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward adorning, of Plating the Hair, and of Wearing of Gold, or of putting on of Apparel; but the Ornantent of a meek and quiet Spirit, which is in the ſight of God of great Price: For after this manner in the old time, the Holy Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men alſo who truſted in God adorned themſelves. — And doth not even Nature it ſelf teach you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.14.</note> 
               <hi>that if a Man have long Hair, it is a ſhame unto him.</hi> And we are not to be conformed to this World,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.2, 17. 2 Cor. 8.21. 1 Pet. 1.14.</note> but we are commanded to provide things honeſt in the ſight of all Men; and <hi>as obedient Children, not faſhioning your ſelves according to the former Luſts, in your Ignorance: But as he which hath called you is Holy, ſo be ye Holy in all Manner of Converſation;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.32.</note> and to <hi>give none offence, neither to the Jews nor to the Gentiles, nor to the Church of God.</hi> But as the Apoſtle ſaith, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever things are true,<note place="margin">Phil. 4.8.</note> honeſt, juſt, pure, lovely, of good report, if there be any Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and if there be any Praiſe, think on theſe things. Now from theſe Scriptures, we may conclude, that tho' our preſent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive faſhions are not all expreſly forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:50130:39"/>yet if any kind of adornings are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited, and if thoſe Texts were written for our Inſtruction, as I think none can doubt thereof, or be ſo bold to deny it, that have any Sence of true Religion; then ſurely they require all the Saints, both Men and Women, at leaſt to abſtain from all thoſe exceſſes in Apparel which are not of good report among ſober Men, and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever putteth on ſuch Attire or Ornaments of Apparel, as are not of good honeſt and modeſt report, they are guilty of breaking the Commandments of Chriſt, and ſo are to be dealt withal by the Church as diſorderly Perſons, who bring a ſcandal upon their Holy Profeſſion.</p>
            <p>Beſides, it is not only a grief for ſober Chriſtians to ſee ſuch Pride of Spirit appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their Communion, but its alſo a ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling to others which are well inclined, to walk in the ways of the Lord with them, as I have found by my own experience: For when I was firſt awakened to ſeek the Lord, and the good of my Soul, the extravagant Dreſſes of ſome Profeſſors among whom I heard the Goſpel preached, occaſioned me to think there was the leſs Religion in them, and that they looked not as if they were Chriſts People; and for this cauſe alone (I having then no Light in Goſpel-Ordinances of Communion) I departed to another Church, which appeared more like ſober Chriſtians, and there I have continued about five and twenty years. And conſidering the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:50130:40"/>ſaith, the Lord hateth a proud look — And God reſiſteth the proud,<note place="margin">Prov. 6.16, 17. Jam. 4.6. 1 Pet. 5.5. Math. 16.24. Rom. 6.4.</note> but giveth Grace unto the Humble: And that the Commandments of Chriſt require our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity in all things ſuitable to his Name and Truth, and thoſe Holy and Self-denying Principles we profeſs, how can ſuch exceſſes in Apparel which even gives their Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lie, conſiſt with their ſincere Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to him?<note place="margin">Jam. 2.18.</note> How do they ſhew their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Faith therein by their Works, but rather as it is ſaid of her that liveth in Pleaſure, that ſhe is dead while ſhe liveth.<note place="margin">Gal. 6.7.</note> 
               <hi>Be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, God is not mocked, for whatſoever a Man ſoweth, that ſhall he alſo reap. For he that ſoweth to his Fleſh, ſhall of the Fleſh reap Corruption: but he that ſoweth to the Spirit, ſhall of the Spirit reap Life Everlaſting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude, our Baptized Churches that are for particular Election and final Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance in the ſame Faith and Order of the Goſpel in full Communion together; they (nor many others) have not any Reaſon to reflect on the true deſign of this Treatiſe, or on the Matters contained therein, as any ways tending to the Interruption of our Peace, on the ſettled Principles of our Churches, but to the purging out the leaven of unrighteouſneſs, that may be found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them; nor can any Perſon in our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion appear againſt the plain Contents of this Treatiſe, but they muſt at the ſame time appear for and Countenance ſuch ſinful Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, Erroneous Doctrine, falſe Worſhip,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:50130:40"/>and corrupt Adminiſtration of Goſpel-Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, as the Word of God, and the general Profeſſion of our Churches does plainly witneſs againſt; and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they will apparently ſhew themſelves oppoſers of Reformation, or ſuch as la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to weaken and confound the Baptiſt Churches and our pure Religion. Yea far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if corrupt Manners which is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly ſinful by the Moral Law of God, or ſuch Erroneous Doctrine, falſe Worſhip, or irregular Adminiſtrations of Goſpel Ordinances as are prohibited our Communion by the Holy Scriptures, ſhould be knowingly ſuffered therein, it is a viſible Mark of Degeneration; and thereby the Church partakes of the Sins of particular Members, <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.17. <hi>Thou ſhalt not hate thy Brother in thine Heart, thou ſhalt in any wiſe rebuket thy Neighbour, and not ſuffer Sin upon him:</hi> Or as it is in our Margin, <hi>that thou bare not Sin for him.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to <hi>Timothy, Lay Hands ſuddenly on no Man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.22.</note> 
               <hi>neither be partakers of other Mens Sins, keep thy ſelf Pure.</hi> Beſides, it is ſhewed before, what warrant and command we have in the New Teſtament, for withdrawing our Communion in the aforeſaid Caſes of Sin, and from diſorderly Perſons: And therefore when a Church perſiſteth in a wilful neglect of this Duty, ſhe brings her ſelf under the guilt of Sin for breaking of Chriſts Commandment; but in Caſe this were faithfully performed, yet the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:50130:41"/>Church ſhould ſtill endeavour,<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 3.14, 15. Tit. 3.10.</note> by due ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhing of ſuch Offenders, to reduce them to their Obedience; and if no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance be found,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.12. 1 Cor. 5.4, 5. 1 Tim. 1.20.</note> ſhe ought to proceed to a farther Act of Authority, and cut them wholly off from her fellowſhip.</p>
            <p>But if any plead, that ſo ſtrict a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, as hath been argued for in this Treatiſe, cannot be duely obſerved with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out indangering their Church-ſtate: It deſerves our Noting, either as a Carnal Reflection on the Holy and Righteous Precepts of Chriſt, and on his Wiſdom, as not preſcribing ſuch Laws which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth moſt to the Glory of God, and the good of his People here on Earth; or it is a ſign that ſuch a Church has been ſo long in the neglect of their Duty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Chriſt and one another; and are ſo far degenerated in their Spirits, as that they ſeem to be paſt recovery: And if this be the State of ſome, who perhaps may have as high a Conceit of themſelves as the Church of the <hi>Laodiceans</hi> had, and ſay,<note place="margin">Rev. 3.17, 18, 19.</note> 
               <hi>I am Rich, and increaſed with Goods, and have need of nothing; and knoweſt not that thou art wretched, and miſerable, and poor, and blind, and naked;</hi> Chriſt coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelleth ſuch to buy of him <hi>Gold tried in the Fire, that thou mayeſt be rich, and white Raiment, that thou mayeſt be Cloathed, and that the ſhame of thy Nakedneſs do not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, and anoint thine Eyes with Eye-Salve, that thou mayeſt ſee.</hi> And ſaith our Lord,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:50130:41"/>
               <hi>As many as I love, I rebuke and chaſten: Be zealous therefore and repent;</hi> leaſt he come and fight againſt thee with the Sword of his Mouth. Behold,<note place="margin">Rev. 2.16.</note> (ſaith he) <hi>I ſtand at the Door and knock: If any Man hear my Voice, and open the Door, I will come in to him, and will ſup with him, and he with me.</hi> Be not afraid therefore to go about this good work of Reformation, do thy Duty and leave the ſucceſs to God, whoſe Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing you may expect, and whoſe awful preſence may ſo far attend the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Chriſt by which you Act, as to ſtop the Mouth of carnal Reaſonings; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that inſtead of indangering the loſs of your Church-ſtate,<note place="margin">Math. 16.18. Jam. 4.8, 9, 10.</note> you may rather ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, and find the Lord will ſtrengthen, eſtabliſh and ſettle it on the Rock of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, againſt which the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail.</p>
            <p>To cloſe, Altho' I have uſed the Word [withdraw] in the Caſe of a Private Members removing Communion from a Church, which may not be done in ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn a Manner as when a Church with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draws her Communion from a Member; (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this is done by an Act of Duty and Authority given to the Body, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is done as an Act of Liberty and Duty pertaining to a Member, and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted by the Scriptures, as hath been ſhewed;) yet the Word withdraw, being it ſelf of a harmleſs and indifferent Signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, it cannot be excepted againſt; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:50130:42"/>it be for want of other Matters to Cavil at: However I have alſo this to ſay that the Word [with-draw] was thought proper to be uſed in the ſame Caſe in the Congregationals twenty eighth Article of the Inſtitution of Churches before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENTS.</head>
            <p>THere is Publiſhed by the ſame Author, a Book Intitled, <hi>Truth ſoberly Defended,</hi> in a ſerious Reply to Mr. <hi>B. Keach</hi>'s Book called, <hi>The Breach Repaired in Gods Worſhip, &amp;c.</hi> As alſo a Vindication of a Book, Intitled, <hi>Prelimited Forms of Praiſing God, vocally Sung by all the Church together, proved to be no Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-Ordinance;</hi> with a Narrative, wherein is detected Mr. <hi>Keach</hi>'s Abuſes, under the Hands of ſeveral Elders and other Brethren. By <hi>Iſaac Marlow,</hi> Price Bound 1<hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is likewiſe Publiſhed, a Treatiſe of the <hi>Holy Trin unity,</hi> Aſſerting the Deity of Jeſus Chriſt and the Holy Spirit in the Unity of Eſſence with God the Father. By <hi>I Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low,</hi> Price Bound 9 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover there is Publiſhed, <hi>A Tract on the Sabbath day,</hi> wherein the keeping of the Firſt-day of the Week a Sabbath is juſtified, by a Divine Command and a Double Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, contained in the Old and New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By <hi>Iſaac Marlow,</hi> Price 1<hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
